<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Janua scientiarum, or, A compendious introduction to geography, chronology, government, history, phylosophy, and all genteel sorts of literature by Charles Blount ...</title>
            <author>Blount, Charles, 1654-1693.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1684</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 149 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 76 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A28438</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3306</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R2203</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12076208</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12076208</idno>
            <idno type="VID">53633</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A28438)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 53633)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 860:5)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Janua scientiarum, or, A compendious introduction to geography, chronology, government, history, phylosophy, and all genteel sorts of literature by Charles Blount ...</title>
                  <author>Blount, Charles, 1654-1693.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 135 p., [1] folded p. of plates : ill.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nath. Thompson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1684.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Geography --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Chronology.</term>
               <term>Political science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Philosophy --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:53633:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Janua Scientiarum:</hi> OR, A COMPENDIOUS INTRODUCTION TO
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Geography,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Chronology,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Government,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hiſtory,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Phyloſophy,</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
And all Genteel ſorts of LITERATURE</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> CHARLES BLOUNT <hi>Gent.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>— Brevis eſſe Laboro.</q>
            <p>Printed by <hi>Nath. Thompſon</hi> at the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the <hi>Old-Spring-Garden</hi> near <hi>Charing-Croſs,</hi> MDCLXXXIV.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:53633:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:53633:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>To His GRACE, Charles Lenox, DUKE of RICHMOND, EARL of MARCH, BARON of SHEDRINGTON, Maſter of the Horſe TO HIS MOST Sacred Majeſty, And Knight of the moſt Noble Order of the GARTER.</p>
            <p>This Piece is moſt humbly Dedicated by the Author, CHARLES BLOUNT.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:53633:3"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 2. line 5. read <hi>Corcica,</hi> p. 2. l. 9. r. <hi>Stepha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus,</hi> p. 31. l. 16. after <hi>Luxury</hi> put <hi>the,</hi> p. 32. l. 3. r. <hi>Aſtyages,</hi> p. 40. l. 16. r. <hi>Antoninus,</hi> p. 42. l. 16. r. <hi>Conſtantinus,</hi> p. 43. l. 5. r. <hi>Heruli,</hi> p. 45. l. 16. r. <hi>Lygdanus,</hi> p. 61. l. 21. r. <hi>Antoninus Pius,</hi> p. 61. l. 22. r. <hi>Aurelius Antoninus,</hi> p. 62. l. 19. r. <hi>Scythia,</hi> p. 63. l. 4. after <hi>whom</hi> r. <hi>he,</hi> p. 64. l. 6. r. <hi>Antoninus,</hi> p. 66. l. 11. after <hi>rather</hi> r. <hi>a,</hi> p. 70. l. 17. r. <hi>Arnuphis,</hi> p. 75. l. 8. for <hi>Vices</hi> r. <hi>Virtues,</hi> p. 77. l. 9. r. <hi>paſſages,</hi> p. 79. l. 20 for <hi>it</hi> r. <hi>them.</hi> p. 80. l. 6. for <hi>Porſona</hi> r. <hi>Porſenna,</hi> p. 80. l. 22. r. <hi>agreeably,</hi> p. 95. l. 15. after <hi>attribute</hi> r. <hi>to,</hi> p. 103. l. 6. r. <hi>Senecaes,</hi> p. 104. l. 6. r. <hi>of the Cimbri,</hi> p. 105. l. 2. r. <hi>Pieces,</hi> p. 108. l. 2. r. <hi>Antoninus,</hi> p. 108. l. 14. for <hi>one of</hi> r. <hi>one and,</hi> p. 112. l. 7. r. <hi>Eclipſes,</hi> p. 117. l. 18. r. <hi>Wat Tylor,</hi> p. 126. l. 13. r. <hi>Petronius,</hi> p. 135. l. 19. r. <hi>quaſi;</hi> in the great ſheet <hi>Saeſar</hi> for <hi>Caeſar.</hi> For theſe and what other faults occurre; the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor entreats the Generous Reader to impute them to his remote Abode from the Preſs.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:53633:3"/>
            <head>BOOKS Printed and Sold by <hi>Nathaniel Thompſon</hi> at the Entrance into the <hi>Old-Spring-Garden</hi> near <hi>Charing-Croſs.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>A Narrative of the <hi>Phanatical Plot,</hi> ſetting forth the Treaſonable and Wicked Deſigns which they have been carrying on againſt King &amp; Government ever ſince the laſt <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. With an Account of the Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cherous Contrivances againſt ſeveral Worthy Perſons, and the Meaſures which they uſed to take off the Kings-Evidence by <hi>Subornation.</hi> To which is added, A Relation of the Evil Practices of <hi>John Rowſe</hi> (who was lately Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Tyburn,) William Lewis,</hi> (who ſtands Convicted,) and others. By <hi>John Zeal</hi> Gent. Price 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:53633:4"/>A Vindication of the Lord <hi>Ruſſel</hi>'s Speech and Innocence; In a Dialogue betwixt <hi>Whig</hi> and <hi>Tory:</hi> Being the ſame that was Promiſed to the <hi>Obſervator</hi> in a <hi>Penny-Poſt-Letter.</hi> Price 4 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stafford</hi>'s Memoirs: Or, a Brief and Impartial Account of the Birth and Quality, Impriſonment, Tryal and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples, Declaration, Comportment, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion; Laſt Speech and Final End of <hi>WILLIAM</hi> late Lord Viſcount <hi>STAFFORD,</hi> Beheaded on <hi>Tower-hill Wedneſday</hi> the 29th. of <hi>December</hi> 1680. Whereunto is annexed a ſhort Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dix concerning ſome Paſſages in <hi>Stephen Colledges</hi> Tryal at <hi>Oxford.</hi> Price Bound 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 6. <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>The Lawyer Out-law'd; Or a Brief Anſwer to Mr. <hi>Hunt</hi>'s Defence of the <hi>Charter.</hi> With ſome Uſeful Remarks on the Commons Proceedings in the laſt Parliament at <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> In a Letter to Friend. Price 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oates</hi>'s Manifeſto; or the Complaint of <hi>TIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S OATES</hi> againſt the Doctor
<pb facs="tcp:53633:4"/>
of <hi>Salamanca:</hi> And the ſame DOCTOR againſt <hi>TIT<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S OATES;</hi> Compriz'd in a Dialogue between the ſaid Parties, on occaſion of ſome Inconſiſtent Evidence given about the Horrid and Damnable <hi>POPISH PLOT.</hi> Price 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>A LETTER to Mr. <hi>Elkana Settle,</hi> oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned upon his Famous Recanting and <hi>Plot-Ridiculing</hi> Narrative. Price 4 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>Some Brief <hi>Remarks</hi> on the Debates of the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> in the laſt Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament at <hi>Oxford,</hi> &amp;c. Price 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Badger</hi> in the <hi>Fox-Trap,</hi> or a Satyr upon Satyr; An Excellent new Satyr. price 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>The Arraignment of <hi>Co-Ordinate-Power;</hi> wherein all Arbitrary-proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are laid open to all Honeſt Abhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and Addreſſers: with a Touch at the <hi>London Petition</hi> and <hi>Charter,</hi> &amp;c. very uſeful for all Lawyers and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men. Price 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:53633:5"/>An Anſwer to a Scandalous Pamphlet, Entituled, <hi>A Character of a Popiſh Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor, and what</hi> England <hi>may expect from ſuch a One.</hi> Price 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>The GENEALOGIES of the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>born Prince and Princeſs, GEORGE and ANNE, of <hi>Denmark, &amp;c.</hi> Shewing the Lineal Deſcent of theſe two Noble and Illuſtrious Families: with Their <hi>Matches, Iſſue, Times of Death, Place of Sepulcher, Impreſses, Devices,</hi> &amp;c. From the Year of Grace M. to this preſent Year 1683. <hi>Extracted from the most Authentick Teſtimonies of the beſt Hiſtorians and An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquaries of Their times.</hi> Price bound 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anima Mundi:</hi> Or, An Hiſtorical Narration of the Opinions of the An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients concerning Man's Soul after this Life; according to Un-enlightned Nature.</p>
            <p>Great is <hi>Diana</hi> of the <hi>Epheſians:</hi> Or, the Original of <hi>Idolatry;</hi> Together with the Politick Inſtitution of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> Sacrifices. Both Bound together, price 1 <abbr>
                  <hi>s.</hi>
               </abbr> 6 <abbr>
                  <hi>d.</hi>
               </abbr> Both written by <hi>C. Blount</hi> Gent.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_kings">
            <pb facs="tcp:53633:6"/>
            <list>
               <item>Kings of The firſt ASSYRIAN <hi>or</hi> BABYLONISH MONARCHY. (which began An<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. M. 1788 <hi>&amp; laſted</hi> 1646 <hi>yeares) were</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>NIMROD.
<list>
                           <item>Belus</item>
                           <item>Ninus or Aſhur</item>
                           <item>Semiramis</item>
                           <item>Ninias</item>
                           <item>Arius <hi>&amp; others we known till</hi>
                           </item>
                           <item>Sardanapalus <hi>After whom y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Empire was di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided by Rebellion An<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. M. 3148 between</hi>
                              <list>
                                 <head>MEDIA</head>
                                 <item>Arbaces</item>
                                 <item>Mandanes</item>
                                 <item>Soſarmus</item>
                                 <item>Articas</item>
                                 <item>Cardicias</item>
                                 <item>Deioces</item>
                                 <item>Phraortes</item>
                                 <item>Cyaxares</item>
                                 <item>Aſty ages <hi>by Succeſsion</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                              <list>
                                 <head>BABYLON</head>
                                 <item>Beleſus</item>
                                 <item>Tiglah-Peleſar</item>
                                 <item>Salmanaſar</item>
                                 <item>Senacherib</item>
                                 <item>Aſſarhaddon</item>
                                 <item>Merodach-Baladan</item>
                                 <item>Nebuchadnezzar</item>
                                 <item>Evil Merodack</item>
                                 <item>Belſhazar. <hi>by Conqueſt</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>Kings of the ſecond <hi>or</hi> PERSIAN MONARCHY, (which began An<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. M. 3434 <hi>and laſted, 228 yeares) were</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>CYRUS
<list>
                           <item>Cambyſes</item>
                           <item>Darius Hyſtaspes</item>
                           <item>Xerxes</item>
                           <item>Artaxerxes Longimanus</item>
                           <item>Darius Nothus</item>
                           <item>Artaxerxes Mnemon</item>
                           <item>Artaxerxes Ochus</item>
                           <item>Arſames</item>
                           <item>Darius Codomannus <hi>Overcome by</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:53633:7"/>The firſt King of the third GRECIAN <hi>or</hi> MACEDONIAN MONARCHY, (<hi>w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>. began</hi> An<hi rend="sup">o</hi>. M. 3642 <hi>&amp; laſted</hi> 300 <hi>yeares) were</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>ALEXANDER THE GREAT.
<list>
                           <head>Who dying without ſons after him the Empire was divided into theſe foure parts.</head>
                           <item>
                              <list>
                                 <head>MACEDON</head>
                                 <item>
                                    <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                       <desc>•</desc>
                                    </gap>ridaeus Brother <hi>of</hi> Alex: M.</item>
                                 <item>Caſsander</item>
                                 <item>Phillippus</item>
                                 <item>Antipater</item>
                                 <item>Demetrius Poliorcetes</item>
                                 <item>Pyrrhus King <hi>of</hi> Epirus</item>
                                 <item>Lyſimachus</item>
                                 <item>Ptolomaeus Ceraunus</item>
                                 <item>Meleager</item>
                                 <item>Anti-pater <hi>the 2<abbr>
                                          <hi rend="sup">d</hi>.</abbr>
                                    </hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Soſthenes</item>
                                 <item>Antigonus Gonatus</item>
                                 <item>Demetrius <hi>the 2<abbr>
                                          <hi rend="sup">d</hi>.</abbr>
                                    </hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Antigonus Doſon</item>
                                 <item>Phillipus <hi>the 2<abbr>
                                          <hi rend="sup">d</hi>.</abbr>
                                    </hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>Perſeus <hi>who being Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come By Paulys Emylius y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Roman Conſul, Macedon was herby reduced into a Province Under the ROMANS: Who An<hi rend="sup">o</hi>: M: 3924 began</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <list>
                                 <head>ASIA MINOR</head>
                                 <item>1 Antigonus Phil: <hi>of Macadon<hi rend="sup">s</hi>. Baſtard</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 Demetrius Poliorcetes <hi>Who being expell'd by his Son in Law</hi> Seleucus Nica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor. <hi>Aſia was thereupon A next to</hi> Syria, <hi>and by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sequence fell, Ioyntly with</hi> Syria <hi>under y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Dominion of The ROMANS: Who An<hi rend="sup">o</hi>: M: 3924 began</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <list>
                                 <head>SYRIA</head>
                                 <item>1 Seleucus Nicanor</item>
                                 <item>2 Antiochus Soter</item>
                                 <item>3 Antiochus Theos</item>
                                 <item>4 Seleuchus Callinachus</item>
                                 <item>5 Seleuchus Ceraunus</item>
                                 <item>6 Antiochus Magnus</item>
                                 <item>7 Seleucus Philopater</item>
                                 <item>8 Antiochus Epiphanes</item>
                                 <item>9 Antiochus Eupater</item>
                                 <item>10 Demetrius Soter</item>
                                 <item>11 Alexander Bala</item>
                                 <item>12 Demetrius Nicanor</item>
                                 <item>13 Antiochus Entheus</item>
                                 <item>14 Tryphon</item>
                                 <item>15 Antiochus Sidetes</item>
                                 <item>16 Demetrius Nicanor, redux</item>
                                 <item>17 Alexander Zebenna</item>
                                 <item>18 Antiochus Grypus</item>
                                 <item>19 Tygranes <hi>who being ſubdued by</hi> Pompey, <hi>Syria after that became a Province. Under the ROMANS: Who An<hi rend="sup">o</hi>: M: 3924 began</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <list>
                                 <head>EGYPT</head>
                                 <item>1 Ptolomeus lagus Phil: <hi>Baſtard of Mace<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                                          <desc>•</desc>
                                       </gap>
                                    </hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>2 Ptolom: Philadelphus</item>
                                 <item>3 Ptolom: Evargetes</item>
                                 <item>4 Ptol: Philopater</item>
                                 <item>5 Ptol: Epiphanes</item>
                                 <item>6 Ptolo: Philometor</item>
                                 <item>7 Ptolo: Phyſcon</item>
                                 <item>8 Ptolom: Lamyrus</item>
                                 <item>9 Ptolom: Alexander</item>
                                 <item>10 Ptol: Lamyrus redux</item>
                                 <item>11 Ptol: Auletes</item>
                                 <item>12 Ptolom Dijoniſius</item>
                                 <item>13 Cleopatra (<hi>Daughter of</hi> Ptolom: Auletes) <hi>who was not only y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Beloved Miſtreſs of</hi> Julius Saeſar, <hi>but alſo of Mark Anthony, whoſe Over throw at</hi> Actium <hi>made her in deſpair throw away her Life by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Biting of an</hi> Aſp <hi>&amp; by her Death Egypt was alſo reduced into a Province Under the ROMANS: Who An<hi rend="sup">o</hi>: M: 3924 began</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <pb facs="tcp:53633:8"/>firſt Period of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fourth MONARCHY, <hi>or ROMAN EMPIRE (w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>. reach'd to</hi> Conſtantine y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Great, <hi>&amp; laſted</hi> 355 <hi>yeares) under</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. JULIUS CAESAR
<list>
                           <item>2 Auguſtus</item>
                           <item>3 Tiberius</item>
                           <item>4 Caligula</item>
                           <item>5 Claudius</item>
                           <item>6 Nero</item>
                           <item>7 Galba</item>
                           <item>8 Otho</item>
                           <item>9 Vitellius</item>
                           <item>10 Flavius Veſpaſian</item>
                           <item>11 Tytus Veſpaſian</item>
                           <item>12 Domitian</item>
                           <item>13 Nerva</item>
                           <item>14 Trajanus</item>
                           <item>15 Adrianus</item>
                           <item>16 Antoninus Pius</item>
                           <item>17 Antoninus Phyloſophus</item>
                           <item>18 Commodus</item>
                           <item>19 Pertinax</item>
                           <item>20 Didius Julianus</item>
                           <item>21 Septimius Severus</item>
                           <item>22 Carracalla</item>
                           <item>23 Macrinus</item>
                           <item>24 Heliogabalus</item>
                           <item>25 Alexand: Severus</item>
                           <item>26 Maximinus Thrax</item>
                           <item>27 Balbinus, &amp; Puppienus</item>
                           <item>28 Gordianus</item>
                           <item>29 Phillippus Arabs</item>
                           <item>30 Decius</item>
                           <item>31 Tribonianus Gallus</item>
                           <item>32 Valerian</item>
                           <item>33 Galienus</item>
                           <item>34 Claudius Secundus</item>
                           <item>35 Aurelianus</item>
                           <item>36 Tacitus</item>
                           <item>37 Probus</item>
                           <item>38 Carus</item>
                           <item>39 Dyocleſian and</item>
                           <item>40 Conſtantius Chlorus, <hi>The Father of</hi> Conſtantine the Great, <hi>Who Removing y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Seat of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Empire from Rome to Byzantium in Greece, did there after his one Name Erect Conſtantinople, where (as Hiſtorians reckon) began (A. Ch. 306) y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Empire of the Eaſt.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="1" type="book">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:53633:9"/>
            <head>
               <hi>LIB.</hi> I. OF GEOGRAPHY.</head>
            <p>Qu. <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat is</hi> Geography?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Globe of the Earth; and differs from <hi>Topography,</hi> (which is the deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of particular places) as the whole differs from a part.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Into how many parts is the Earth divided?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Into four;
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Europe,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aſia,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Africa,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>America</hi> both</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:53633:10"/>Qu. <hi>Which are the chief Countreys of</hi> Europe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Europe</hi> may be divided into theſe three parts:</p>
            <p n="1">I. on the Continent,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Scandinavia,</hi> which comprehends</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sweden, Denmark,</hi> and <hi>Norway;</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Muſcovy,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>or <hi>Ruſſia,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>France,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Germany,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Poland,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Spain,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Italy,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>part of <hi>Turkey.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. The <hi>Britiſh-Iſles;</hi> as, <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. Iſles on the Mediterranean; as,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sardinia,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Candia,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sicily,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Corcia,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Majorca,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Minorca.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which are the chief Countreys of</hi> Aſia?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Aſia</hi> may be divided alſo into three parts; as,</p>
            <p n="1">I. On the Continent,
<list>
                  <item>part of <hi>Turkey,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Georgia,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Arabia,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Perſia,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>India,</hi> or <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guls Countrey,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>China,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Tartaria.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:53633:10"/>II. Iſles on the Ocean; as,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Maldivies,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ceylan,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Sunda,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Molucques,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Philippines,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Japan.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. Iſles on the Mediterranean; as,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cyprus,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rhodes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Scio,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Metelin.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which are the chief Countreys of</hi> Africa?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Africa</hi> in like manner may be divided into three parts; as,</p>
            <p n="1">I. On the Continent,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Barbary,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aegypt,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Biledulgerid,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Zaara,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Countrey of <hi>Negroes,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Guiney,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Nubia,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Abiſſinea,</hi> or <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thiopia,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Zanguebar,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Congo,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Monomotapa,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Caffares.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. Iſles on the Ocean; as,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Madera,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Canaries,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Cape Verde,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>St. <hi>Thomas,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>St. <hi>Helena,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Madagaſcar,</hi> or</item>
                  <item>St. <hi>Lawrence,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>and <hi>Zocotora.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. an Iſle on the Mediterranean-Sea, called <hi>Malta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:53633:11"/>Qu. <hi>Which are the chief Countreys of</hi> America?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Which <hi>America</hi> do you mean? for it is uſually divided in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>North</hi> and <hi>South.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which then are the chief parts of the Northern</hi> America?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Northern <hi>America</hi> may likewiſe be divided into three parts; as, I. On the Continent,
<list>
                  <item>the <hi>Arctickland,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>New north Wales</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>New ſouth Wales</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>New Britain,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Canada,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>New France,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>New Scotland,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>New England,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>New York,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>New Jerſey,</hi> or</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pennſylvania,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mary-Land,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Virginia,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Carolina,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Florida,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mexico,</hi> or <hi>New Spain,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>New Mexico,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Land of <hi>Jeſſo,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>and <hi>Anian.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. Iſles on the North Sea; as, <hi>New-found-land,</hi> and the <hi>Antilles,</hi> which comprehend <hi>Jamaica,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with all the <hi>Lucaif</hi> and <hi>Caribbe-Iſles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:53633:11"/>III. an Iſland in the South Sea, na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med <hi>California.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which are the chief parts of the Southern</hi> America?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Southern <hi>America</hi> (ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepting one Iſland, called <hi>Magella<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick</hi>) is all a Continent, having in it theſe ſeveral Countreys, <hi>viz.</hi> the firm Land,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Magellan,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Peru,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Amazones,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Chili,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Braſil,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Paraquay.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is a</hi> Continent?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> A <hi>Continent</hi> is one great parcel of Land, wherein are many Countreys joyned together, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out being ſeperated by the Sea.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is an</hi> Iſland?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> An <hi>Iſland</hi> is any part of Earth encompaſſed round with Water; as, <hi>Great Britain</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Of what extent or circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence is the Earth judged to be?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Geographers divide the Globe into 360 parts or degrees;
<pb facs="tcp:53633:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
So that reckoning each Degree to be 73 <hi>Italian</hi> miles, or 69 <hi>Engliſh,</hi> (which is the ſame) its Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence will appear to be 26286 miles, and its Diameter 8365 miles.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Of what ſcituation and extent is</hi> Europe?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Europe</hi> is for the moſt part ſcituate in the Northern Temperate <hi>Zone,</hi> and contains within its bounds the principal part of the <hi>Roman</hi> and <hi>Graecian</hi> Monarchies: whoſe length, from <hi>Cape-finis-terre</hi> on the weſt of <hi>Spain,</hi> to the River <hi>Ianais</hi> in <hi>Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covy,</hi> is 2400 miles; and breadth, from <hi>Cape-Metapan</hi> in <hi>Morea,</hi> to the moſt Northern Promontory of <hi>Norway,</hi> about 2100 miles.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How is</hi> Europe <hi>bounded?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Europe</hi> is bounded on the North with the Northern Ocean, or frozen Sea; on the Weſt with the Weſtern or <hi>Atlantick</hi> Ocean; on the South, with the Mediterra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nean Sea, parting <hi>Europe</hi> from <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca;</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:53633:12"/>
and laſtly, on the Eaſt, it is divided from <hi>Aſia</hi> by the Rivers <hi>Duina</hi> and <hi>Tanais.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Of what ſcituation and extent is</hi> Aſia?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Aſia</hi> (from whence ſprang the firſt Monarchies and Religions of the World, and now poſſeſs'd by four the greateſt Princes of the Earth, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the Grand Seignior, Sultan of <hi>Perſia,</hi> Great Mogul, and Cham of <hi>China</hi> and <hi>Tartary:</hi>) is ſeated moſtly in the Temperate Zone: and extends in length, from <hi>Smyrna</hi> in the Weſt, to the fartheſt part of <hi>Tartary</hi> near <hi>Jeſſo</hi> in the Eaſt, about 4800 miles; and in breadth, from the loweſt part of <hi>Malacca</hi> in the South, to the Streights of <hi>Wei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gats</hi> in the <hi>North,</hi> near 4200 miles.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How is</hi> Aſia <hi>bounded?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Aſia,</hi> on the weſt, is ſepera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from <hi>Africa</hi> by the Red-Sea, and by the <hi>Iſtmhus</hi> of <hi>Sues;</hi> from <hi>Europe,</hi> by the Rivers <hi>Tanais</hi> and
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:53633:13"/>
               <hi>Duina;</hi> and towards the other part of the World, is environ'd by the <hi>Tartarian, Chinean, Indian, Perſian,</hi> and <hi>Arabian</hi> Seas.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Of what ſcituation and extent is</hi> Africa?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Africa</hi> is ſcituated under the Torrid <hi>Zone:</hi> being in length, from <hi>Cape-Verde</hi> to <hi>Gaardafuy,</hi> 4300 miles; and in breadth, from <hi>Cape-Bon</hi> to the <hi>Cape of good-hope,</hi> 4200 miles.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How is</hi> Africa <hi>bounded?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Africa</hi> is formed like a Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle, and ſeperated from all parts of the World but <hi>Aſia</hi> by four Seas: being limited, on the North, by the Mediterranean; on the Eaſt, by the Red-Sea, or <hi>Arabian-Gulph;</hi> on the South, by the <hi>Aethiopian;</hi> and on the Weſt, by the <hi>Atlantick</hi>-O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cean.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How is</hi> America <hi>bounded?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. America</hi> (the fourth and laſt known part of the World, which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:53633:13"/>
               <hi>Columbus</hi> firſt diſcovered 190 years ago) is bounded on the Eaſt, by the <hi>Atlantick</hi> and <hi>Vergivian</hi> Seas, which part it from <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Africa;</hi> on the Weſt, by <hi>Mare Pacificum,</hi> which divides it from <hi>Aſia;</hi> on the South, by <hi>Terra incognita,</hi> ſeperated by the Streights of <hi>Magellan;</hi> and on the North, by parts as yet undiſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red: ſo as no extent thereof can certainly be given.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Now, foraſmuch as it concerns all</hi> Europeans <hi>to have a more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular knowledge of</hi> Europe, <hi>as well as of the chief Towns in other parts of the World, wherewith we trade: pray tell me firſt, how many Cities and Pariſhes there are in</hi> England, <hi>together with its extent, circumference and limits?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> In <hi>England</hi> there are twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-five Cities, whereof <hi>London, York, Briſtol,</hi> and <hi>Norwich,</hi> are the four chief. Alſo it is divided into fifty-two Shires or Counties, and thoſe again into 9725 Pariſhes: being in
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:53633:14"/>
length, from <hi>Barwick</hi> in the North, to the <hi>Iſle of Wight</hi> in the South, 386 miles; and from <hi>Dover</hi> in the Eaſt, to the Lands-end in <hi>Cornwal</hi> in the Weſt, about 279 miles; and 1300 miles in compaſs round about. Laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it is bounded on the South with <hi>Normandy</hi> and <hi>France,</hi> on the Eaſt with <hi>Germany</hi> and <hi>Denmark,</hi> on the Weſt with <hi>Ireland,</hi> and on the North with <hi>Scotland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which are the chief Cities or Towns in</hi> France; <hi>and how is it divided?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. France</hi> may be divided into three parts; 1. the Inland, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning theſe Provinces, <hi>(viz.)</hi> the <hi>Iſle of France, Champagne, Orleanois, Burgundy, Lyonnois,</hi> and <hi>Dauphine.</hi> 2. on the Ocean, as are <hi>Picardy, Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandy, Bretagne, Guienne,</hi> and <hi>Gaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coigne.</hi> 3. and laſtly, on the Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranean, <hi>Languedock</hi> and <hi>Provence.</hi> As for the chief Cities or Towns of <hi>France,</hi> they are theſe; <hi>Paris, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:53633:14"/>
Lyons, Bourdeaux, Tholouſe, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chel, Aix, Grenoble, Diion, Metz, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miens, Orleans, Marſeilles</hi> and <hi>Nants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How is</hi> Italy <hi>divided; and which are its principal Cities and Towns?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Italy</hi> is likewiſe uſually di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into three parts; 1. the Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, which comprehends the State of the Church, and State of <hi>Tuſcany.</hi> 2. <hi>Lombardy,</hi> which conſiſts of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice, Milan, Genuoa, Parma, Mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, Mantua, Trente, Lucca,</hi> and <hi>Piedmont.</hi> 3. and laſtly, the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremes of <hi>Italy;</hi> as, <hi>Naples, &amp;c.</hi> which ſeveral parts are beautified with theſe moſt eminent Cities and Towns, <hi>Rome, Venice, Milan, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, Turin, Genoa,</hi> and <hi>Florence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How is</hi> Spain <hi>divided;</hi> and <hi>which are its moſt eminent Cities or Towns?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Spain</hi> is divided into five parts, 1. the Inland, conſiſting of <hi>Caſtile</hi> and <hi>Leon.</hi> 2. the North-part,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:53633:15"/>
which contains <hi>Galicia, Aſturies, Biſcay</hi> and <hi>Navarre.</hi> 3. the Eaſt, comprehending <hi>Arragon, Catalogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>a,</hi> and <hi>Valencia.</hi> 4. in the South are, <hi>Murcia, Granada,</hi> and <hi>Andalouſia.</hi> 5. and laſtly, in the Weſt are, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guares</hi> and <hi>Portugal.</hi> The moſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Cities are, <hi>Madrid, Toledo, Burgos, Lisbon, Sevil, Granada, Valencia, Barcelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na, Salamanca, Caragoza, Leon,</hi> and <hi>Cadiz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How is</hi> Germany <hi>divided; and which are its chief Towns?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Germany</hi> may be divided into three parts; the firſt belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> which contains <hi>Austria, Stiria, Carinthia, Carniola, Tirol, Bohemia, Sileſia, Moravia, Luſatia, French-County,</hi> and the Catholick Provinces called <hi>Flanders.</hi> 2. that part divided a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Princes of the Empire; as, the <hi>Palatinate on the Rhine,</hi> the <hi>Eccleſiastick Electorates, Franconia,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:53633:15"/>
Heſſe, Westphalia, Bavaria, Sovabe, upper-Saxony, Brandenburg, Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rania,</hi> and <hi>lower-Saxony.</hi> 3. and laſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces;</hi> as, <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Zealand, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>tretch, Guelderland, Zutphen, Overyſſel, Frieſland,</hi> and <hi>Groningen.</hi> As for the chief Cities and Towns belonging to theſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral parts of <hi>Germany,</hi> they are theſe, <hi>Vienna, Prague, Cologne, Francfort, Hamburg, Nurembourg, Antwerp, Bruſſels, Ghent, Amſter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> and the <hi>Hague.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How is</hi> Poland <hi>uſually divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; and which are its moſt eminent Towns?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is divided into ſeveral Provinces, whereof the chief are, the great and leſſer <hi>Polands,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>Mozavia, Pruſſia, &amp;c.</hi> As for its Towns, the moſt eminent are, <hi>Cracovia, Warſaw,</hi> and <hi>Dant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How is</hi> Turkey <hi>in</hi> Europe <hi>divided; and which are its chief Cities?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:53633:16"/>
               <hi>Anſ. Turkey</hi> in <hi>Europe</hi> may be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into three parts; as 1. the North Provinces, which are, <hi>Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia, Servia, Bulgaria, Boſnia, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garia, Croatia,</hi> and <hi>Dalmatia.</hi> 2. South Provinces; as, <hi>Macedonia, Epirus, Theſſalia, Achaia,</hi> and <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea,</hi> or <hi>Peleponeſus.</hi> 3. and laſtly, <hi>Tranſilvanian</hi> Provinces; as, <hi>Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilvania, Valachia, Moldavia,</hi> and <hi>petit Tartars.</hi> As for the chief Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in the <hi>Europaean Turkey,</hi> they are theſe ſeven, <hi>Conſtantinople, Adria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople, Sophia, Buda, Belgrade, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonichi,</hi> and <hi>Miſiſtra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How is</hi> Muſcovy <hi>divided; and which is its chief City and Town?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Muſcovy,</hi> or <hi>Ruſſia,</hi> (which is all one) may be divided into two parts, North and South, compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hending ſeveral Principalities and Dukedoms, together with one Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick, called <hi>North-Lapland.</hi> The chief City of <hi>Muſcovy</hi> is <hi>Moſcow,</hi> but its chief Harbour and place of trade <hi>Arch-Angelo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:53633:16"/>Qu. <hi>How may</hi> Sweden <hi>be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded; and which are its chief Towns?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Sweden</hi> is divided into ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny conſiderable Provinces; as, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Gothland, Weſt-Lapland, Fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Livonia,</hi> and others: whereof the capital Cities are, <hi>Stockholm</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pſal</hi> in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pland,</hi> and <hi>Calmar</hi> in <hi>Gothland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How may</hi> Denmark <hi>and</hi> Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way <hi>be divided; and which are their chief Towns?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Denmark</hi> and <hi>Norway</hi> are now two Kingdoms united under one Monarch: to which we may add <hi>Greenland</hi> and the Iſles of <hi>Ferro</hi> and <hi>Iſeland.</hi> The chief Towns are, <hi>Copenhagen</hi> in <hi>Denmark,</hi> and <hi>Ber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ghen</hi> in <hi>Norway.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which are the chief Towns in</hi> Scotland?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Edinburgh, St. Andrews, Glaſcow, Sterling, Dunbritton, Falk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Perth,</hi> and <hi>Aberdeen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How is</hi> Ireland <hi>divided?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:53633:17"/>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Into four Provinces, <hi>(viz.) Leinster, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lster, Munster,</hi> and <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naugh;</hi> In which Provinces are 32 Counties.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which are the chief Cities in</hi> Ireland?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Dublin, Waterford, Galloway, Limrick, Kingſale, Cork, London<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derry</hi> and <hi>Armagh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is a</hi> Peninſula?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Peninſula, <hi>quaſi pene inſula,</hi> almoſt an Iſland, is a part of Land, which being almoſt encompaſſed round with Water, is yet joyned to the firm land by ſome little <hi>Iſtmhus,</hi> or neck of Earth; as <hi>Africa</hi> is joyn'd to <hi>Aſia; Peleponeſus</hi> or <hi>Morea</hi> to <hi>Greece; Molucca</hi> to <hi>India; Jutland</hi> to <hi>Holſatia;</hi> and <hi>Corea</hi> to <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is an</hi> Iſtmhus?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> An <hi>Iſtmhus</hi> is any narrow neck of Land betwixt two Seas, joyning the Peninſula to the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent; as that betwixt <hi>Aegypt</hi> and
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:53633:17"/>
               <hi>Arabia,</hi> which parts <hi>Aſia</hi> from <hi>Afri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca;</hi> and thoſe of <hi>Panama</hi> and <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riene</hi> in <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is a</hi> Promontory?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> A <hi>Promontory</hi> is an high Hill or Mountain, that ſhoots it ſelf out as an Elbow of Land into the Sea, the utmoſt extent whereof is call'd a <hi>Fore-land,</hi> or <hi>Cape;</hi> as, the <hi>Cape of good-hope</hi> in the furtheſt part of <hi>Africa,</hi> by which thoſe paſs that ſail into <hi>India:</hi> Alſo <hi>Cape-Verde</hi> in <hi>Africa,</hi> the <hi>Cape of Victory</hi> at the mouth of the <hi>Magellanie Seas,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Cape of S. Vincent</hi> in <hi>Portugal,</hi> with many other.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which are the most eminent Hills or Mountains upon Earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thoſe of moſt note are, the <hi>Pyrenaean Hills</hi> betwixt <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain, Mount Cenis</hi> and the <hi>Alps</hi> betwixt <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Italy, Mount Atlas</hi> in <hi>Mauritania, Mount Athos</hi> in <hi>Macedon, Mount Caucaſus</hi> in <hi>India, Mount Olympus</hi> in <hi>Theſſaly, Mount Taurus</hi> in <hi>Aſia, Mount Apennine</hi> in
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:53633:18"/>
               <hi>Italy,</hi> and laſtly, <hi>el Pico</hi> in <hi>Tenariff</hi> near the <hi>Canary Iſles,</hi> thought to be the higheſt in the World, being 15 miles high, and viſible 100 miles off at Sea. Now, beſides all theſe, there are many other Mountains, no leſs fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for their vomiting up of Fire, than for their heighth; as, <hi>Aetna</hi> in <hi>Sicily, Veſuvius</hi> near <hi>Naples</hi> in <hi>Italy, Hecla</hi> in <hi>Iſeland,</hi> and many others of the like nature in the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lucca</hi> and <hi>Japaneſe Iſlands,</hi> as well as in <hi>Peru, Braſil, Congo</hi> and the <hi>Azores.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which are the chief</hi> Deſarts?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thoſe of <hi>Lybia</hi> in <hi>Africk,</hi> that encompaſs <hi>Aegypt;</hi> as alſo thoſe in <hi>Arabia, Tartarie, Nova Zembla, Norway, Lapland, Finmarch, Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, Germany</hi> and <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Where are the beſt Gold and Silver Mines?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> In <hi>Peru, Arabia, Guinea, Monomotapa, Japan, Perſia, China, Chili,</hi> and <hi>Potoſi,</hi> from whence the <hi>Spaniards</hi> have yearly exhauſted 12 millions.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:53633:18"/>Qu. <hi>Having given this general ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of the</hi> terra firma, <hi>and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar (becauſe moſt neceſſary) relation of</hi> Europe: <hi>let us in the next place launch into the Ocean, and examine the watry World; for which end, inform us, how the ſeveral ſorts of Waters may be diſtinguiſhed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Into <hi>Seas, Streights, Lakes,</hi> or <hi>Rivers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which are the chief Seas?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The <hi>Levant,</hi> or Eaſt Sea; the Weſt, North and South Seas; the <hi>Baltick</hi> Sea; the <hi>Red</hi> Sea; the <hi>Aethiopian</hi> Sea; the Mediterranean Sea; the <hi>Archipelago;</hi> St. <hi>George</hi>'s Sea; the <hi>Euxine</hi> Sea; and the <hi>Dead,</hi> or <hi>Caſpian</hi> Sea, on our Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinent; together with the <hi>Magel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanick</hi> and <hi>Mare-pacificum</hi> on the Continent of <hi>America.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is a</hi> Streight?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> A Streight or Gulph is any narrow part or arm of the Ocean, lying between two ſhoars, and ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:53633:19"/>
a way into the Sea, as, the Streights of <hi>Jeſſo,</hi> lying between the two Continents; the Streights of <hi>Magellan,</hi> between North and South <hi>America;</hi> the Streights of <hi>Gibralter</hi> on the Coaſt of <hi>Spain,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Africa;</hi> the Streights of <hi>Babelmandel,</hi> between <hi>Aſia</hi> and <hi>Africa;</hi> the Gulph of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice</hi> and the Bay of <hi>Biſcay</hi> in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is a</hi> Lake?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> A Lake is any place that continually retains ſtanding-water in it, as <hi>Laggo Major</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> the Lake of <hi>Lucerna,</hi> and <hi>Geneva</hi> in <hi>Switzerland, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is a</hi> River?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> A River is any ſmall branch of the Sea flowing up into a Land; as, the <hi>Thames, Severn, Trent</hi> and <hi>Humber</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> the <hi>Seine, Loyre</hi> and <hi>Rhoſne</hi> in <hi>France;</hi> the <hi>Rhine</hi> and <hi>Elbe</hi> in <hi>Germany;</hi> the <hi>Po</hi> and <hi>Tyber</hi> in <hi>Italy;</hi> the River
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:53633:19"/>
               <hi>Volga</hi> of <hi>Muſcovy,</hi> the greateſt in <hi>Europe;</hi> the <hi>Danube</hi> of <hi>Turkey</hi> in <hi>Europe; Euphrates, Tigris</hi> and <hi>Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan</hi> of <hi>Turkey</hi> in <hi>Aſia;</hi> the <hi>Indus</hi> and <hi>Ganges</hi> of <hi>India;</hi> and the <hi>Nile</hi> of <hi>Aegypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which are the beſt Authors for</hi> Geography?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Ptolomy, Strabo, Stephanuus, Ortelius, Mercator, Scaliger, Ferra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, Varenius</hi> and <hi>Munster;</hi> with <hi>Bleau</hi>'s, <hi>Johnſon</hi>'s and <hi>Sanſon</hi>'s Maps.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="2" type="book">
            <head>
               <hi>LIB.</hi> II. OF CHRONOLOGY.</head>
            <p>Qu. <hi>WHat is</hi> Chronology?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Chronology</hi> is the knowledge of Times paſt.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is an Age, or Century?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The ſpace of an hundred years.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:53633:20"/>Qu. <hi>In what Age of the World was our</hi> Saviour <hi>born?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> About the middle of the one and fortieth Age.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is a Year?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It conſiſts of twelve months, and is the ſpace of time wherein the Sun paſſes thorow the twelve Signs of the <hi>Zodiack.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is the</hi> Zodiack?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> An imaginary great Circle in the Heavens, which (as Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers pretend) containeth the twelve Signs.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Name the twelve Signs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Aries, Taurus, Gemini, Cancer, Leo, Virgo, Libra, Scorpio, Sagitari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Capricornus, Aquarius,</hi> and <hi>Piſces.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is that which the</hi> Greeks <hi>call</hi> Galaxia, <hi>the</hi> Latines, Via Lactea, <hi>and we, the</hi> Milky-way?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 'Tis nothing but a number of little Stars, which give but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed light, and are not perceptible to the eye without a Proſpective-glaſs.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:53633:20"/>Qu. <hi>How many days are there in a year?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Three hundred three ſcore and five days and ſix hours, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to <hi>Caeſar</hi>'s Reformation of the Kalendar.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What becomes of theſe odd ſix hours that remain every year?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Why, in the ſpace of four years they make up a day; ſo that every fourth year hath one day more then ordinary, and is therefore called <hi>Biſſextile,</hi> or <hi>Leap-year.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is a Month?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Of months there are two ſorts; Firſt, a <hi>Lunary</hi> month, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of four weeks, which is the ſpace of time wherein the Moon paſſes thorow the twelve Signs of the <hi>Zodiack;</hi> and ſecondly, a <hi>Sola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> month, conſiſting of thirty days, ten hours and an half, the ſpace of time wherein the Sun paſſes thorow the twelfth part, or one Sign of the <hi>Zodiack.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:53633:21"/>Qu. <hi>How many days are there in each</hi> Solary <hi>month?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Thirty days hath <hi>September, April, June,</hi> and <hi>November; February</hi> hath twenty eight alone, And the reſt have thirty one.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How did the Ancients divide their months?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Into <hi>Calends, Nones</hi> and <hi>Ides;</hi> calling the firſt day of every month the <hi>Calends.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How did the Ancients divide their weeks?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Into ſeven days, which they called by the name of the ſeven Planets; the <hi>Sun,</hi> the <hi>Moon, Mars, Mercury, Jupiter, Venus</hi> and <hi>Saturn.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What makes the Day and Night?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> When the Sun is above the Horizon, it makes day; and when it is under the Horizon, it makes night.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What are the</hi> Aequinoxes <hi>and</hi> Solſtices?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:53633:21"/>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> There are yearly two <hi>Aequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noxes</hi> and two <hi>Solſtices;</hi> a <hi>Vernal</hi> and <hi>Autumnal</hi> Aequinox, and a <hi>Summer</hi> and <hi>Winter</hi> Solſtice, which begin the four ſeveral ſeaſons of the year. The <hi>Aequinoxes</hi> are ſo called from the <hi>Latine</hi>-word <hi>Aequinoctium,</hi> becauſe the days and nights are then of equal length, the Sun riſing and ſetting at ſix, which is upon the 10<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>March</hi> and 12<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>September.</hi> Alſo the <hi>Solſtices</hi> are named from the <hi>Latine</hi>-word <hi>Solstitium,</hi> which ſignifies a ſtop of the Sun; becauſe, as it comes no nearer us than the Tropick of <hi>Cancer</hi> in the Summer, ſo goes it not further from us than the Tropick of <hi>Capricorn</hi> in the Winter; which Summer-<hi>Solſtice,</hi> as it makes the longeſt day on the 11<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>June,</hi> ſo doth the Winter-<hi>Solſtice</hi> make the ſhorteſt day on the 11<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> of <hi>December.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What makes the ſeveral Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of the Moon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:53633:22"/>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Moon ſhines more or leſs according to the proportion of light it receives from the Sun. As for example: We call it <hi>New Moon</hi> when it is in conjunction with the Sun; and then it gives us no light, becauſe the dark part of it is to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards us: But four days after it makes its firſt appearance in the ſhape of two bright Horns, (the reſt of her Body being dark) and then is the <hi>firſt quarter.</hi> Being a week old, half of it appears bright, and the other half dark; at which time it is called a Creſcent, or <hi>Half-moon.</hi> Thus it increaſes a week more, till it comes to be <hi>Full;</hi> and then being diametrically oppoſite to the Sun, this ſtrikes its Beams upon that more fully, till four days after full Moon it begins to decreaſe, and loſe its light, which is called the <hi>Wain;</hi> three days after which, it appears in the form of a Creſcent; and ſo loſes its light gradually till <hi>New Moon</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:53633:22"/>Qu. <hi>What makes an Eclipſe of the Sun?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The interpoſition of the Moon betwixt the Sun and the Earth, which happens when the Moon is the ſame Sign and Degree with the Sun; for then the Sun, Moon and Earth are diametrically oppoſite.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What makes an Eclipſe of the Moon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The interpoſition of the Earth betwixt the Sun and the Moon, which happens generally up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the full of the Moon; at which time this Planet is diametrically op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the Sun.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is an</hi> Epocha?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is ſome remarkable point of time, from the which Chronolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers begin to reckon, in reference to the changes of their own Nation: Thus, the <hi>Jews</hi> reckoned, from their departure out of <hi>Aegypt;</hi> the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> from their Olympiads inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:53633:23"/>
by <hi>Iphitus;</hi> The <hi>Romans,</hi> from the building of their City; the Chriſtians, from the Birth of Chriſt; and the <hi>Turks,</hi> from their <hi>Hegira,</hi> or flight of <hi>Mahomet.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is a Luſtre, and an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lympiad?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> A <hi>Luſtre</hi> among the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> and <hi>Olympiad</hi> among the <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians,</hi> ſignified the ſpace of five years: becauſe the Games ſo called were celebrated every fifth year.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How do Sacred Chronilogers begin to reckon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, from the Creation to <hi>Noah</hi>'s Flood, 1657 years.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. From the Flood to the cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of <hi>Abraham,</hi> 367 years.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. From the calling of <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> to the departure of the <hi>Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>elites</hi> out of <hi>Aegypt,</hi> 430 years.</p>
            <p n="4">4ly. From the <hi>Aegyptians Exodus,</hi> to <hi>Solomon</hi>'s building of the firſt Temple, 480 years.</p>
            <p n="5">5ly. From the building of the firſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:53633:23"/>
Temple, to the erection of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond by <hi>Zorobabel,</hi> 497 years.</p>
            <p n="6">6ly. From the building the ſecond by <hi>Zorobabel,</hi> to the Birth of our Saviour Chriſt, 529 years.</p>
            <p n="7">7ly. and <hi>laſtly,</hi> From the Birth of our Saviour, to theſe preſent times, 1683 years.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How do Prophane Chronolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers begin to reckon?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, From <hi>Nimrod</hi> to <hi>Cyrus</hi> the Great, 1646 years.</p>
            <p n="2">2dly. From <hi>Cyrus</hi> to <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, 228 years.</p>
            <p n="3">3dly. From <hi>Alexander</hi> to <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> 300 years.</p>
            <p n="4">4ly. From <hi>Caeſar</hi> to <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, 355 years.</p>
            <p n="5">5ly. From <hi>Conſtantine</hi> to <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, 455 years.</p>
            <p n="6">6ly. From <hi>Charles</hi> the Great to <hi>Radulphus</hi> of <hi>Auſpurgh,</hi> 472 years.</p>
            <p n="7">7ly. and <hi>laſtly,</hi> From <hi>Radulphus</hi> to theſe preſent times, 400 years.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which are the beſt Authors for Chronology?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:53633:24"/>
               <hi>Anſ. Helvicus, Calviſius, Buchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cer, Funccius, Petavius, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> and <hi>Alſtedius.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="3" type="book">
            <head>
               <hi>LIB.</hi> III. OF HISTORY.</head>
            <div type="monarchy">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the</hi> Aſſyrian MONARCHY.</head>
               <p>Qu. <hi>WHat is</hi> Hiſtory?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> A Record of paſt actions, either Sacred or Civil.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>Which are the four chief and moſt ancient Monarchies of the World?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The <hi>Aſsyrian,</hi> the <hi>Perſian,</hi> the <hi>Grecian</hi> and the <hi>Roman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder what Kings did the</hi> Aſſyrian <hi>Monarchy begin, flouriſh and expire?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It began under <hi>Nimrod,</hi> and
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:53633:24"/>
flouriſh'd till <hi>Sardanapalus,</hi> by whoſe Luſt it was divided, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt deſtroy'd.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>At what time was the</hi> Aſſyrian <hi>Monarchy founded, and how long did it laſt?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It was founded about ſeven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen hundred years after the Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and laſted ſixteen hundred forty ſix years longer.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>Tell me the Names of the</hi> Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian <hi>Kings in order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ. Nimrod, Belus, Ninus,</hi> or <hi>Aſhur, Semiramis, Ninias, Arius,</hi> and others unknown, till we come to <hi>Sardanapalus,</hi> by whoſe Luxury Monarchy became divided between two Rebels, <hi>Arbaces</hi> and <hi>Beleſus,</hi> and ſo continued to them and their Heirs till <hi>Cyrus</hi>'s time, who began the ſecond Monarchy, called the <hi>Perſian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>How came</hi> Cyrus <hi>to begin the ſecond Monarchy?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="32" facs="tcp:53633:25"/>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> One part of the Empire fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to him by ſucceſſion from his Grandfather <hi>Aſtygas,</hi> (one of <hi>Arba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi>'s Succeſſors) he ſoon conquered <hi>Belſhazzer,</hi> (who was <hi>Beleſus</hi>'s Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſor) and ſo joyning both parts of the Empire together, began a new Monarchy in <hi>Perſia,</hi> his Native-Countrey.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>Wat Authors treat of this</hi> Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyrian <hi>Monarchy?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The holy Scriptures, <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus, Diodorus, Siculus, Juſtin, Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſebius, Matthaeus, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher, Raleigh, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el</hi> and <hi>Viginier;</hi> beſides the ancient <hi>Cteſias, Beroſus</hi> and <hi>Megaſtenes,</hi> whereof only ſome few fragments remain.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="monarchy">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:53633:25"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the Second,</hi> OR PERSIAN MONARCHY.</head>
               <p>Qu. <hi>WHy was this ſecond Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy called the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy of the</hi> Medes <hi>and</hi> Perſians?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe the Empire did chiefly conſiſt of thoſe two King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nder what Kings did this</hi> Perſian <hi>Monarchy begin, flouriſh and expire?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It began under <hi>Cyrus,</hi> whoſe Race ended in his Son <hi>Cambyſes;</hi> after whom, <hi>Darius Hyſtaſpes,</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving defeated the <hi>Magi,</hi> and won the Empire from his Competitors by the neighing of his Horſe, it ſtill flouriſhed till <hi>Darius Codomanus,</hi> in whom it ended.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:53633:26"/>Qu. <hi>How long did this ſecond, or</hi> Perſian <hi>Monarchy last?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It laſted 228 years, and was enjoyed only by two Families, that of <hi>Cyrus,</hi> and that of <hi>Darius Hyſtaſpes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>Tell me the Names of the</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian <hi>Kings in order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cyrus the Great,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Cambyſes,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Darius Hyſtaſpes,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Xerxes,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Artaxerxes Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gimanus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Darius Nothus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Artaxerxes Mne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Artaxerxes Ochus</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Arſames;</hi> and laſtly,</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Dar. Codomanus,</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>What Authors write chiefly of this ſecond Monarchy?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ. Herodotus, Thucydides, Xe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nophon, Plutarch, Diodorus, Justin</hi> and <hi>Oroſius.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="monarchy">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:53633:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the Third,</hi> OR GRECIAN MONARCHY.</head>
               <p>Qu. <hi>WHy was this Third Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy call'd the</hi> Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an <hi>or</hi> Macedonian <hi>Monarchy?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It was ſo called from its firſt Founder, <hi>Alexander,</hi> the Son of King <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon,</hi> a <hi>Grecian</hi> born.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>When was it that</hi> Alexander <hi>began to reign?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 329 years before the Birth of Chriſt, and in 12 years ſpace con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd moſt part of the Univerſe; and is therefore called, <hi>the Great.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>How long did the</hi> Grecian <hi>Monarchy flouriſh?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> It flouriſh'd no longer than <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Life; for he dying without Sons, bequeath'd the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire to the Worthieſt; which cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:53633:27"/>
great diviſion amongſt the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, till at length they divided it into four parts: And ſo it laſted till they were all conquer'd by the <hi>Romans,</hi> who began the <hi>Fourth</hi> and laſt Monarchy, under the Conduct of <hi>Julius Caeſar.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>Which were the Four parts of this</hi> Grecian <hi>Monarchy, after its di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Kingdoms of <hi>Macedon, Aſia minor, Syria</hi> and <hi>Aegypt;</hi> all which were in the ſpace of 300 years reduced to the <hi>Roman</hi> Yoak.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>What Kings ſucceeded in</hi> Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon <hi>after</hi> Alexander?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The firſt was <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Brother <hi>Arideus;</hi> after whom ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded fifteen Kings more, whereof the laſt was <hi>Perſeus,</hi> who was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come by <hi>Paulus Aemylius,</hi> the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Conſul.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>What Kings ſucceeded in</hi> Aſia minor <hi>after</hi> Alexander?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> But Two; whereof the
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:53633:27"/>
firſt was <hi>Antigonus,</hi> King <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi>'s Baſtard, and the ſecond was <hi>Demetrius Poliorcetes,</hi> who be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing put to flight by his Son-in-law <hi>Seleucus Nicanor;</hi> after that, <hi>Aſia minor</hi> was joyn'd to the Kingdom of <hi>Syria.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>What Kings ſucceeded in</hi> Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria <hi>after</hi> Alexander?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The firſt was <hi>Seleucus Nica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor,</hi> after whom ſucceeded 19 King, whereof the laſt was <hi>Tigranes,</hi> who being ſubdued by <hi>Pompey, Syria</hi> became a Province to the <hi>Romans.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>Now laſtly, What Kings ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded</hi> Alexander <hi>in</hi> Aegypt?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The firſt was <hi>Ptolomaeus Lagus,</hi> (another of King <hi>Philip</hi>'s Baſtards) after whom ſucceeded 12 Princes more, till by the death of the famous <hi>Cleopatra, Aegypt</hi> was reduced into a <hi>Roman</hi> Province; And thus <hi>Rome,</hi> having ſwallowed up the four diviſions of the <hi>Grecian</hi> Monarchy, began another, which
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:53633:28"/>
was called the <hi>Fourth,</hi> or <hi>Roman.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>Which are the best ancient Authors that treat of this</hi> Grecian <hi>Monarchy?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Arrianus</hi> and <hi>Quintus Curtius,</hi> that write of <hi>Alexander</hi> himſelf; and ſecondly, <hi>Plutarch, Juſtin, Polybius</hi> and <hi>Diodorus,</hi> that treat concerning his Succeſſors.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="monarchy">
               <head>
                  <hi>Of the Fourth,</hi> OR, ROMAN MONARCHY.</head>
               <p>Qu. <hi>WHen was</hi> Rome <hi>firſt founded, and by whom?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ. Rome</hi> was firſt built 753 years before Chriſt, by the two Brothers, <hi>Romulus</hi> and <hi>Rhemus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>How hath</hi> Rome <hi>been ancient<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly govern'd?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ. Rome</hi> was firſt govern'd ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively by Kings; then by annual
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:53633:28"/>
Conſuls, limited with Senators and Tribunes; and in time of War or diſtreſs, by Dictators, who beco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming perpetual, were at laſt called <hi>Emperours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>How many were the firſt Kings of</hi> Rome? <hi>name them in order.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Seven; to wit, <hi>Romulus, Numa Pompilius, Tullius Hoſtilius, Ancus Martius, Tarquinius Priſcius, Servius Tullius,</hi> and <hi>Tarquinius Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbus,</hi> who by reaſon of his Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny was the laſt King of the <hi>Romans;</hi> after whom they govern'd by Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuls till the Emperours times.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>Who was the first</hi> Roman <hi>Emperour?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ. Julius Caeſar,</hi> who making himſelf perpetual Dictator, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving defeated <hi>Pompey,</hi> took upon him the ſole government of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, and ſo began the fourth Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, called the <hi>Roman,</hi> which was afterwards eſtabliſhed by <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gustus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:53633:29"/>Qu. <hi>How many years was it from the building of the City of</hi> Rome, <hi>to the death of</hi> Julius Caeſar?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> 710 years; which was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 42 years before the Birth of Chriſt, who was 14 years old when <hi>Auguſtus</hi> dy'd.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>The firſt period of this</hi> Roman <hi>Empire, reaching from</hi> Julius Caeſar <hi>to</hi> Conſtantine <hi>the Great, tell me in order the Names of the ſeveral Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Auguſtus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tiberius,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Caligula,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Claudius,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nero,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Galba,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Otho,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Vitellius,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Flavius Veſpaſian,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Titus Veſpaſian,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Domitian,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Nerva,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Trajanus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Adrianus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Antonius Pius,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Anton. Phyloſoph.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Commodus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Pertinax,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Didius Julianus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Septimius Severus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Caracalla,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Macrinus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Heliogabalus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb n="41" facs="tcp:53633:29"/>
                        <hi>Alexander Severus</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Maximinus Thrax</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Balbinus</hi> &amp; <hi>Pup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pienus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Gordianus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Philippus Arabs,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Decius,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tribonianus Gallus</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Valerian,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Galienus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Claudius ſecund'</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Aurelianus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Tacitus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Probus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Carus,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Diocleſian,</hi> and</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Conſtantius Chlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras,</hi> Father of</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>How many years was it from</hi> Julius Caeſar <hi>to</hi> Conſtantine <hi>the Great?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> About 355 years.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>Why is the firſt period of the</hi> Roman <hi>Empire reckon'd but to</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine <hi>the Great, when he had ſo many conſiderable Emperours that ſucceeded him, as</hi> Conſtantius, Julian the Apoſtate, <hi>and others?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, becauſe <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great was the firſt Chriſtian Emperour; and ſecondly, becauſe he removed the Imperial Seat from <hi>Rome</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> to <hi>Byzantium</hi> in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:53633:30"/>
                  <hi>Greece:</hi> where building a great City he call'd it after his own Name, <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> which ſoon after produced a diviſion of the Empire into <hi>Eaſt</hi> and <hi>Weſt,</hi> betwixt <hi>Arca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dius</hi> and <hi>Honorius;</hi> and ſo it conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued for ſeveral years under two ſeveral Emperours.</p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>What became of the Empire of the</hi> Eaſt, <hi>after its diviſion?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Empire of the <hi>Eaſt,</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with its chief City, <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinople,</hi> was taken by the <hi>Turks</hi> (who now poſſeſs it) about 230 years a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go, from the laſt <hi>Greek</hi> Emperour, <hi>Conſtantius Palaeologus;</hi> whereupon 'tis obſerv'd, that as the City of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople</hi> was built by a <hi>Constan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine</hi> the firſt, whoſe Mothers Name was St. <hi>Helena,</hi> ſo likewiſe was it loſt under a <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the eleventh, whoſe Mothers Name alſo was <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lena.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>What became of the Empire of the</hi> Weſt, <hi>which was held at</hi> Rome, <hi>after</hi> Honorius?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:53633:30"/>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> About 100 years after <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norius,</hi> the Empire of the <hi>Weſt</hi> was deſtroy'd, together with its Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Auguſtulus,</hi> by <hi>Odoacer</hi> King of the <hi>Herulii;</hi> which Empire hath been ſince ſucceeded by two Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions of Weſtern Franks: the firſt beginning with <hi>Charles</hi> the Great, and the ſecond with <hi>Radulphus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpurgenſis</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>Austria,</hi> who poſſeſſes the <hi>German</hi> Empire at this preſent time. But here it is obſervable, how that as the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire was founded by an <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> ſo was it loſt by an <hi>Auguſtulus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>How was the</hi> Roman <hi>Empire deſtroy'd?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> By the Invaſion of <hi>Barbari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> ſuch as were the <hi>Hunns, Goths</hi> and <hi>Vandals.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Qu. <hi>Which are the beſt Writers of this Fourth, or</hi> Roman <hi>Monarchy?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ. Caeſar</hi>'s <hi>Commentaries, Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius Halicarnaſſeus, Valerius Maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Livy, Plutarch, Suetonius, Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus,</hi>
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:53633:31"/>
both the <hi>Plinies, Velleius Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terculus, Ammianus Marcellinus, Appian, Lucius Florus, Herodian, Polybius, Dion Caſſius, Saluſt, Zozi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus, Procopius, Jornandes, Caſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus, Agathias, Hiſtoriae Auguſtae Scriptores,</hi> and all the <hi>Byzantine</hi> Writers, beſides many learned mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Authors of the ſame Subject.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="4" type="book">
            <head>
               <hi>LIB.</hi> IV. OF THE GREEK and ROMAN HISTORIANS.</head>
            <p>Qu <hi>WHich are the moſt eminent of the</hi> Greek <hi>Hiſtorians?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Herodotus, Thucydides, Xe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nophon, Polybius, Diodorus Siculus. Dionyſius Halicarnaſſeus, Joſephus,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:53633:31"/>
Plutarch, Philostratus, Arrianus, Laertius, Appian, Dion Caſſius, He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodian, Eunapius, Zozimus, Euſebi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> and the <hi>Byzantine</hi> Hiſtorians, as <hi>Procopius, Agathias,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Herodotus?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Herodotus,</hi> born at <hi>Halicar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſſus,</hi> a City in <hi>Greece,</hi> is the moſt ancient of Hiſtorians we have ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant next to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and therefore called by <hi>Cicero, the Father of Hiſtory.</hi> He lived about 450 years before Chriſt; when, being a man of Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Power in his Countrey, and oppoſing <hi>Lydamus,</hi> his Cities Tyrant, he was forced to fly to <hi>Thu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium,</hi> where he wrote thoſe Nine Books of Hiſtory, which Poſterity called by the names of <hi>the Nine Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> and which contained the moſt remarkable Tranſactions of the World during 240 years, beginning from the time of <hi>Cyrus</hi> the firſt King of <hi>Perſia,</hi> and ſo on to <hi>Xerxes</hi>'s
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:53633:32"/>
time, wherein <hi>Herodotus</hi> himſelf li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. As for the Life of <hi>Homer,</hi> (though very ancient, and aſcribed to him) it is thought to have been wrote by ſome other hand. <hi>Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dotus</hi> his Stile (like <hi>Homer</hi>'s) is ſweet and eaſie; his Dialect <hi>Ionick:</hi> Some (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> and <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi>) eſteem him fabulous: but <hi>Camera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius, Stephens,</hi> eſpecially our late Voyages and Diſcoveries, have ſufficiently vindicated him. He dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and was buried at <hi>Thurium.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Thucydides?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Thucydides</hi> was twelve years younger than <hi>Herodotus,</hi> and lived 438 years before Chriſt. Being but a Boy, he wept at the hearing of <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rodotus</hi> repeat his Hiſtory, whereby <hi>Herodotus</hi> preſaged his future parts. He was the Son of <hi>Orolus,</hi> of a Royal Extraction, and married a rich Wife, the King of <hi>Thrace</hi> his Daughter, by which means he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:53633:32"/>
much money both to the <hi>Athenians</hi> and <hi>Lacedemonians,</hi> for good intelligence of their procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings; whereof being well infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, he wrote his Hiſtory, and call'd it, <hi>A poſſeſſion for everlaſting,</hi> which gives an account of the <hi>Peleponeſian</hi> Wars with the <hi>Athenians</hi> for one and twenty years together, in 8 Books, whereof the laſt ſeems uncorrect and unfiniſhed to the former ſeven, which makes ſome think it wrote by his Daughter, others by <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pompus,</hi> but <hi>Voſſius</hi> by <hi>Thucydides</hi> himſelf whilſt he was ſick. His me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod is preferr'd above all others; His Stile pithy, and full of matter; His Dialect moſt pure <hi>Attick.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, <hi>Dyoniſius</hi> accuſes him of uſing obſolete words. His Orations filled with good Argument, but tedious. Laſtly, he was an enemy to Fables, and his Relations moſt faithful; writing only of ſuch things as were acted in his own time and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledg,
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:53633:33"/>
which advantage <hi>Herodotus</hi> wanted.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Xenophon?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Xenophon,</hi> by Birth an <hi>Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nian,</hi> and Son of one <hi>Grillus,</hi> lived 400 years before Chriſt. He was a ſecond <hi>Treſmegistus,</hi> being a great Captain, Phyloſopher and Hiſtorio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grapher. His <hi>Attick</hi> Dialect was ſo pure, that he was called <hi>Apes Atti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca,</hi> and was therefore envy'd and hated of <hi>Plato.</hi> He was ſo generous, that he expoſed the Writings of <hi>Thucydides,</hi> which he might have delivered for his own. <hi>Xenophon</hi>'s Hiſtory treats of 46 years Tranſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of the <hi>Greeks,</hi> and begins where <hi>Thucydides</hi> ended; ſhewing <hi>Alcibiades</hi>'s return to his Countrey, whom <hi>Thucydides</hi> left meditating on that retreat. Alſo <hi>Xenophon</hi> gives us the Enterprize of <hi>Cyrus</hi> the younger (under whom he was a General) againſt his Brother <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taxerxes,</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:53633:33"/>
with the <hi>Grecians</hi> retreat out of <hi>Perſia,</hi> which was afterwards an occaſion of his Baniſhment. His Inſtitution of the Elder <hi>Cyrus</hi> is a moral Romance, and ſhews rather what a Prince ſhould do, than what <hi>Cyrus</hi> really did: there being little true Hiſtory in it, ſave the taking of <hi>Babylon,</hi> and captivating of <hi>Crae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> as appears by the Relation gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven of <hi>Cyrus</hi> in <hi>Justin</hi> and other Hiſtorians. As for the Book <hi>de Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quivocis,</hi> attributed to <hi>Xenophon,</hi> it is an Impoſture of <hi>Annius. His works</hi> (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtom) may teach Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks to all Princes, States-men and Generals;</hi> which made <hi>Scipio</hi> and <hi>Lucullus,</hi> who never went without them, ſucceed accordingly, as <hi>Cice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro</hi> obſerves. A late fooliſh <hi>Italian</hi> Author, without any ground for it, accuſes <hi>Xenophon</hi> of an immodeſt Love for <hi>Ageſilaus,</hi> only becauſe he writes ſo much in his praiſe; but he had learnt too much Morality
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:53633:34"/>
from his Tutor <hi>Socrates,</hi> to commit ſuch an Act.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lybius?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Polybius,</hi> born at <hi>Megalopo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis</hi> a City of <hi>Arcadia,</hi> was the Son of <hi>Lycortas</hi> General of the <hi>Achaians,</hi> by whom both Father and Son were ſent Embaſſadors to <hi>Ptolomaeus Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneus;</hi> and afterwards <hi>Polybius</hi> aſſociated with the <hi>Roman</hi> Conſul, as joynt-Commiſſioner, in the War againſt <hi>Perſeus</hi> King of <hi>Theſſaly.</hi> He wrote his Hiſtory in 40 Books, whereof only the five firſt remain entire, with an Epitome of the 12 next following, to the beginning of the 18<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> Book, which were thought to be epitomized by <hi>Marcus Brutus.</hi> This Hiſtory begins with the ſecond <hi>Punick</hi> War, and contains not only the Events that paſſed betwixt the <hi>Romans</hi> and <hi>Macedonian</hi> Kings, to the end of that Monarchy, but all other the moſt conſiderable actions
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:53633:34"/>
of the World for 53 years; for which reaſon he gives it the Name of <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal.</hi> And for the more compleating hereof, he travell'd himſelf over moſt part of <hi>Europe, Aſia</hi> and <hi>Africa,</hi> being furniſhed with Ships by <hi>Scipio Aemilianus,</hi> who, together with <hi>Lelius,</hi> were his two Boſom-friends; whereupon <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith that he wrote a diſtinct Treatiſe of the War of <hi>Numantia,</hi> waged by his Friend <hi>Scipio,</hi> (to whom he was a Councellor, though not a School-maſter, as ſome would have it. He dy'd in the 82<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> year of his age, which was 230 years before Chriſt. He believ'd nothing of Gods, Heaven or Hell, as appears by his ſixth Book. <hi>Dyoniſius</hi> accuſes his unpolite Stile: <hi>Patricius,</hi> without reaſon, blames his method; and <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy</hi> (notwithſtanding he tranſcribes whole Books of <hi>Polybius verbatim</hi> in his <hi>Decades</hi>) diſ-ingeniouſly terms him only <hi>a Writer not to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed.</hi>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:53633:35"/>
However, (beſides the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern <hi>Caſaubon) Cicero</hi> and <hi>Plutarch</hi> of old did much eſteem him; and <hi>Brutus,</hi> who diſliked <hi>Cicero,</hi> did much admire <hi>Polybius.</hi> Finally, as <hi>Voſſius</hi> obſerves, though inferiour to one or other of the <hi>Greeks</hi> for Elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, yet to none for Civil Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and Military Science.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus Siculus?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Diodorus Siculus,</hi> born at <hi>Agyrium</hi> a Town in <hi>Sicily,</hi> lived to a great age under <hi>Julius</hi> and <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus Caeſar,</hi> about the middle of whoſe Reign he dyed. He ſpent 30 years in writing his <hi>Historical Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brary,</hi> which in 40 Books (whereof we have but 15 extant) comprized the moſt remarkable paſſages of the World for the ſpace of 1138 years, (not reckoning what was compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended in his firſt ſix Books, of thoſe fabulous Times before the War of <hi>Troy;</hi>) which is certainly the beſt
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:53633:35"/>
account of the ancient Heathen My<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thology, we have any where extant. For the perfecting hereof, he tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell'd moſt part of <hi>Europe</hi> and <hi>Aſia,</hi> as well as into <hi>Aegypt. Henry Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phens</hi> was informed that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mainders of this Authors Works were all found in <hi>Sicily,</hi> but how true, I know not. His ſtile is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd (as being a <hi>Sicilian,</hi> and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving in the declining of the <hi>Greek</hi> Tongue) by <hi>Bodin;</hi> His Chronolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gy cenſured by <hi>Pighius</hi> and <hi>Sigoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us;</hi> and <hi>Ludovicus Vives</hi> inveighs againſt his whole Book, for deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing the Antiquity of the World according to the ancient <hi>Caldaean</hi> and <hi>Aegyptian</hi> Records. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, Authors of no leſs Credit, as <hi>Photius,</hi> (who praiſes his Stile) toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with <hi>Pliny, Euſebius, Juſtin Martyr,</hi> and <hi>Stephens,</hi> do at leaſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qualize, if not prefer him to the beſt of the <hi>Greek</hi> Hiſtorians.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:53633:36"/>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyſius Halicarnaſſeus?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Dionyſius</hi> of <hi>Halicarnaſſus</hi> in <hi>Greece,</hi> lived under <hi>Auguſtus</hi> at <hi>Rome,</hi> whither he came ſoon after the end of the Civil-Wars; where, after 22 years abode, (having well inform'd himſelf both from the moſt judicious Books and Men) he wrote his <hi>History of the</hi> Roman <hi>Antiqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties,</hi> in 20 Books, (whereof 11 only are extant.) The whole Work be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan from the Siege of <hi>Troy,</hi> and reached to the firſt <hi>Punick</hi> War, and ended there where <hi>Polybius</hi> began. But the 11 now extant con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with the Government of the <hi>Decemviri,</hi> when the Conſuls re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed their Authority, which was 312 Foundation of <hi>Rome.</hi> He was a ſevere Critick, and cenſures <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, Demoſthenes,</hi> and moſt of the Ancients; alſo a moſt accurate O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rator, as appears by his Compoſition of Rhetorick now in being, but too
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:53633:36"/>
exact and rigorous in his Laws of Eloquence; He too much affected digreſſions in his Hiſtory; alſo he was too credulous and ſuperſtitious in his <hi>Ethnick</hi> Religion, as when he makes a Statue ſpeak, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs, <hi>Photius</hi> praiſes his Stile as moſt Elegant, and ſome prefer him before <hi>Livy;</hi> but <hi>Scaliger</hi> eſteems him before any of the <hi>Latines</hi> for his account of <hi>Roman</hi> Antiquities, both in reſpect of his Chronology and Matter, wherein he is very par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſephus?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Joſephus</hi> the <hi>Jew</hi> was born under <hi>Caligula,</hi> (which was 39 years after Chriſts Incarnation) of Royal Extraction, being deſcended from the High-Prieſts of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> by the Father, and from the Royal Blood of the <hi>Machabees</hi> by the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: He lived alſo under nine Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours. In the 26<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> year of his age
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:53633:37" rendition="simple:additions"/>
he went to <hi>Rome,</hi> and by the aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of <hi>Poppaea (Auguſtus</hi>'s Wife) procured the releaſe of thoſe Prieſts whom <hi>Faelix</hi> had impriſon'd. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, being choſen Captain of the <hi>Galilaeans,</hi> he headed them in their revolt againſt the <hi>Romans</hi> under their General <hi>Veſpaſian:</hi> and being worſted, obſcured himſelf in a Well, where he endured great miſery, till being taken, and brought to <hi>Veſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſian,</hi> he there propheſied of <hi>Veſpaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi>'s coming to the Empire; which ſoon happening accordingly, as alſo interpreting the Prophecy of a <hi>Meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſias</hi> to ſignifie <hi>Veſpaſian</hi> and his Son <hi>Titus,</hi> he was releaſed, and made as a Friend to accompany <hi>Titus</hi> at the taking of <hi>Jeruſalem.</hi> After which, he compoſed ſeven Books of that <hi>Judaick</hi> War, which he preſented to <hi>Titus,</hi> who valued them above all others in his Library. To this he adds his own Life, written by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf; And when he was returned to
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:53633:37"/>
               <hi>Rome</hi> with <hi>Veſpaſian,</hi> he wrote his twenty Books of the <hi>Jewiſh Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities,</hi> beginning from the Creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and ſo on to the 12<hi rend="sup">th.</hi> year of <hi>Neroe</hi>'s Reign. As for his two Books againſt <hi>Apion,</hi> they were to vindi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate the Antiquity and Honour of the <hi>Jews,</hi> from a Work which <hi>Apion</hi> had publiſh'd to the diſadvantage of <hi>Philo</hi> and his Countrey-men. <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> (tho' <hi>Hebrew</hi> was his Mother-Tongue) wrote his Books in <hi>Greek,</hi> (wherein he was moſt perfect) to have them more generally under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood by the <hi>Greeks</hi> and <hi>Romans.</hi> The credit of his Hiſtory is blamed by many; as, <hi>Maldonat, Melchior, Canus, Pererius, Baronius,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, as <hi>Gregory,</hi> who ſays, (in his <hi>Poſthuma</hi>) that <hi>Joſephus deſtroys ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Miracles in Holy-Writ, only to make them ſeem credible.</hi> Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, <hi>Justin Martyr, Euſebius,</hi> St. <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom, Suidas, Calviſius,</hi> and <hi>Scaliger,</hi> prefer him to the beſt of Writers next
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:53633:38"/>
thoſe of the Holy-Writ, as doth the Letters of King <hi>Agrippa</hi> approve him for the trueſt of Authors. As for his Teſtimony of Chriſt in the 22<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> Book of his Antiquities, it is by the moſt judicious Criticks thought to have been inſerted by another hand, though very ancient. <hi>Joſephus</hi> publiſh'd his Writings alſo as well in <hi>Hebrew,</hi> as <hi>Greek.</hi> Finally, <hi>Joſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phus</hi> has not only writ many things contrary to <hi>Moſes,</hi> but alſo omitted many Evangelical Truths; as, the coming of the Wiſe-men to <hi>Judaea,</hi> alſo <hi>Herod</hi>'s Maſſacre of the Infants; and therefore ought to be read with caution. Some (as <hi>Munſter</hi>) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found with this Author, that Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfeit <hi>Joſippus Gorionides</hi> his Wars of the <hi>Jews.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Plutarch?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Plutarch</hi> (who lived under <hi>Domitian</hi> and <hi>Nerva,</hi> but flouriſhed chiefly under <hi>Trajan,</hi> about 100
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:53633:38"/>
years after Chriſt) was born at <hi>Cheronaea</hi> in <hi>Baeotia;</hi> He was a Prieſt of <hi>Apollo,</hi> and both a great Hiſtorian and Phyloſopher. Firſt, as for Hiſtory, he wrote the Lives of 24 Famous <hi>Grecians,</hi> educated at <hi>Sparta</hi> and <hi>Athens;</hi> and of 25 <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans,</hi> bred up under the ſeveral Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments at <hi>Rome:</hi> His <hi>Greek</hi> Lives begin with <hi>Theſeus</hi> King of <hi>Athens,</hi> in the year of the World 2750. and end with <hi>Philopaemenes,</hi> General of the <hi>Achaians,</hi> in the year of the World 3821. which was 121 years before Chriſt. His <hi>Roman</hi> Lives begin with <hi>Romulus</hi> the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Rome,</hi> and end with <hi>Galba</hi> and <hi>Otho,</hi> about 70 years after Chriſt, and 820 from the building the City of <hi>Rome.</hi> Now ſecondly, for his Phyloſophy, contain'd in the Book of his Morals, he learnt it part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly from his Father <hi>Lampras</hi> his O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratory, partly from his Grandfather <hi>Nicarchus</hi> his Phyloſophy, and
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:53633:39"/>
partly by the Converſe of his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Timon,</hi> but moſtly from his <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gyptian</hi> Tutor <hi>Ammonius,</hi> and Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vels into <hi>Aegypt.</hi> He is eſteem'd by all as a moſt wiſe grave Author, both in <hi>Phyloſophy</hi> and <hi>Hiſtory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſtratus?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Philoſtratus</hi> flouriſh'd from <hi>Severus</hi> to <hi>Phillippus:</hi> and at the requeſt of <hi>Julia Auguſta, Severuſes</hi> Wife, (whoſe Secretary he was) wrote the Life of <hi>Apollonius Tya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naeus,</hi> a <hi>Pythagorian Magician,</hi> in eight Books: wherein he followed the Relations of <hi>Damis</hi> the <hi>Aſſy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian,</hi> and <hi>Apollonius</hi> his Aſſociate in his Travels; as alſo the Records of <hi>Maximus</hi> the <hi>Aegaean,</hi> and two others, beſides <hi>Apollonius</hi> his own Teſtament of himſelf, and written with his own hand. From hence <hi>Hierocles</hi> (who is for that cauſe An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered by <hi>Euſebius</hi>) attempts to prefer <hi>Apollonius</hi> before <hi>Chriſt;</hi>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:53633:39"/>
which has rais'd an unjuſt out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry of the <hi>PRIESTS</hi> againſt our Author <hi>Philoſtratus:</hi>
               <note place="margin">☜</note> whoſe Style is Elegant <hi>Greek,</hi> as well as his <hi>Geographical</hi> Deſcriptions, eſpecially of <hi>India,</hi> uſeful, and ſuch as are not to be found in others. But to ſay the worſt of him, <hi>Philoſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus</hi> is (as <hi>Merric Cauſabon</hi> obſerves) (though fabulous, where he would make a God of a <hi>Magician</hi>) yet for ſome ſtrange Relations once ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd falſe, and now approv'd true, well deſerving to be Read.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Arrianus?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Arrianus,</hi> of <hi>Nicomedia</hi> a City in <hi>Bithynia,</hi> was a Prieſt of <hi>Ceres</hi> and <hi>Proſerpine;</hi> and flouriſh'd under the Emperours <hi>Adrians, Antonius, Pius,</hi> and <hi>Marcus Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>relius Antonius.</hi> He was as well a <hi>Phyloſopher</hi> as <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> being Educated under <hi>Epictetus</hi> the <hi>Stoick:</hi> whoſe <hi>Phyloſophy</hi> he collected from
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:53633:40"/>
his Diſcourſes, and afterwards pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed in Writing as an <hi>Enchiridion.</hi> Beſides which, he publiſhed of his own Compoſure, ſeven Books of the Expeditions of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, and an eighth Book of ſo much of the <hi>Eaſt-Indies</hi> as was known in his time. He wrote alſo ten Books of <hi>Alexander</hi>'s Succeſſors, whereof at this day there remains only <hi>Photius</hi>'s Abridgement. He wrote likewiſe four other Tracts, none of which are at this time extant: one of <hi>Timoleon</hi> of <hi>Corinths</hi> Acts in <hi>Sicily:</hi> Another of the Art which <hi>Dion</hi> of <hi>Syracuſe</hi> uſed to free thoſe Countries from the Tyranny of <hi>Dionyſius</hi> the Second: A third of the <hi>Parthians</hi> deſcent from <hi>Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thia</hi> and Wars with the <hi>Romans</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Trajan:</hi> And the fourth, called the <hi>Alanick</hi> Hiſtory; which makes ſome believe him to be the ſame <hi>Arrian</hi> that <hi>Dion</hi> ſays was Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of <hi>Cappadocia</hi> under <hi>Adrian,</hi>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:53633:40"/>
that made War upon the <hi>Alanians.</hi> His <hi>Greek</hi> is ſo Attick and Sweet, that it gave him the name of the new or young <hi>Xenophon,</hi> whom attempted to imitate. Not only <hi>Lucian</hi> and <hi>Photius</hi> of old, but alſo <hi>Scaliger, Voſſius</hi> and <hi>Bodin</hi> of the modern Criticks prefer him to the beſt of the <hi>Greek</hi> Hiſtorians, provided you will pardon his Arro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gance in the middle of his firſt Book, where he boaſts himſelf to exceed all other Authors, as much as <hi>Alexander</hi> excell'd all other Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors. Finally of his eight Books, the only that are extant of him, he profeſſes in the firſt ſeven concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning <hi>Alexander</hi> to follow the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations given him by <hi>Aristobulus</hi> and <hi>Ptolomaeus, Lagus,</hi> their Wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, who were Captains under <hi>Alexander;</hi> and in his other eighth and laſt Book of the <hi>East-Indies,</hi> to follow the <hi>Geography</hi> of <hi>Marinus Tyrius,</hi> who in this point far ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeds <hi>Ptolomy:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:53633:41"/>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Diogenes Laertius?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Diogenes Laertius,</hi> ſo called from <hi>Laerte</hi> a Town in <hi>Cilicia</hi> where he was born, liv'd under <hi>Antonius Pius,</hi> or ſoon after. He wrote the Lives and Apothegms of the <hi>Phyloſophers</hi> in ten Books, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning with <hi>Thales,</hi> and ending with <hi>Epicurus;</hi> whom (being him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf an <hi>Epicurean</hi>) he favours even to a fault, making him place his chief Happineſs in the pleaſures of the mind, and not of the body, which is contrary to the Character given both by <hi>Cicero</hi> and other An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient Authors of <hi>Epicurus.</hi> Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſs from hence <hi>Gaſſendus</hi> (too much enclin'd to this <hi>Epicurian</hi> Sect) takes occaſion to write ſo favour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably of its Founder. However, as <hi>Lactantius</hi> treats only of the Moral <hi>Phyloſophers,</hi> ſo we owe our beſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of Natural <hi>Phyloſophers</hi> to <hi>Laertius;</hi> notwithſtanding <hi>Kecker<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:53633:41"/>
(who is more ſtudious of Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern, than Ancient Writers,) con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns him. Finally, <hi>Ludovicus Vives</hi> tells us, that this Piece was written by <hi>Laertius,</hi> to a woman.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Appian?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Appian</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd thence to <hi>Rome,</hi> where he liv'd (under <hi>Trajan, Adrian,</hi> and <hi>Antoninus Pius,</hi>) at firſt the qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Advocate, but afterwards for his parts preferr'd to be one of the Emperors Proctors. He wrote in 24 Books an Hiſtory Royal, beginning with the taking of <hi>Troy,</hi> and ſucceſs of <hi>Aeneas,</hi> and exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the reign of <hi>Auguſtus;</hi> nay with ſome reflections even to the times of <hi>Trajan.</hi> But of all theſe, we have none at this time extant, ſave his <hi>Punick, Syriack, Parthian, Mithridattick, Spaniſh, Hannibalick, Illyrian,</hi> and Civil VVars of the <hi>Romans:</hi> For as for his <hi>Celtick,</hi> or
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:53633:42"/>
VVar with the <hi>Gauls,</hi> we have none but a fragment thereof left us. His Stile is plain and eaſie; and his Orations moving; his Deſcriptions of his Battails Natural, and full of Military knowledge; for all which, he is much extoll'd by <hi>Photius.</hi> And laſtly, for his method, he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour'd to imitate <hi>Thucydides</hi> and <hi>Saluſt;</hi> but fell far ſhort: In ſo much that 'tis rather Rapſody of things moſt important, than a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued Hiſtory, as <hi>Livyes:</hi> He flatters the <hi>Romans</hi> right or wrong: and as <hi>Bodin</hi> obſerves in many Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations appears too Credulous: Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo <hi>Sigonius</hi> accuſes him of great Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, and many Omiſſions: But what is worſt of all, he inſerts as his own, whole Paragraphs out of <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lybius, Plutarch</hi> and other Antique Authors, without ever acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledging his Theft; which was (I conceive) one great reaſon that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperated <hi>Scaliger</hi> ſo far, as (in his
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:53633:42"/>
Notes upon <hi>Euſebius</hi>) to call <hi>Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pian</hi> a meer Child in Hiſtory.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Dion Caſſius?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Dion Caſſius,</hi> whoſe Sir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name was <hi>Coccius,</hi> or <hi>Cocceianus,</hi> was born at <hi>Nicea</hi> a City of <hi>Bithy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nia,</hi> whither he like wiſe retir'd in his old Age to avoid the <hi>Praetorian</hi> Militia, being adviſed thereto by his Familiar Spirit, or <hi>Daemon,</hi> which directed him in all things, as <hi>Socra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes</hi>'s did him; and diverted him from his former <hi>Phyloſophical</hi> Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and Interpretation of Divine Dreams, (whereof he compos'd a Book) to the writing of Hiſtory. He liv'd under the Tyrannies of <hi>Commodus, Caracalla, Macrinus</hi> and <hi>Heliogabulus;</hi> in whoſe Reigns by the prudent conduct of himſelf, he eſcap'd the loſs either of Life, Goods or Reputation; and arrived ſafely to the peaceable happy Reign of <hi>Alexander Severus,</hi> under whom
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:53633:43"/>
he publiſh'd his <hi>Roman</hi> Hiſtory, being directed thereto by his Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius, as well as commanded by <hi>Septimius Severus.</hi> His Father <hi>Apro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nianus</hi> was a Conſular man, as well as Governour of <hi>Dalmatia,</hi> and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſul of <hi>Cilicia.</hi> Alſo he himſelf having Conſular Dignity twice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed upon him, and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding <hi>Pergamus, Smyrna, Africk, Auſtria,</hi> and <hi>Hungary,</hi> was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards made Joynt-Conſul with the Emperour <hi>Alexander.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Hiſtory comprehends 981. years, <hi>viz.</hi> from the Building of <hi>Rome,</hi> to the Reign of <hi>Alexander Severus</hi> in 80 Books, divided into eight <hi>Decades,</hi> whereof the firſt 34 Books are loſt: Alſo, of the twenty, we have only the Epitomy of <hi>Xiphiline</hi> a <hi>Conſtantiniopolitan</hi> Monk; for all that we have entire of <hi>Dion Caſſius</hi> (beſides this <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendium,</hi>) are only the Events of 300 years, beginning with <hi>Lucullus</hi>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:53633:43"/>
about 71 years before Chriſt, and ending with the Death of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Claudius.</hi> But all this Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors VVritings that are loſt, what are moſt to be lamented, are the 40 laſt years, whereof he was an Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witneſs. He employ'd ten years in providing Materials for his Hiſtory, and twelve more Compoſing it.</p>
            <p>He imitates <hi>Thucydides</hi> in his Narratives and Orations, but not in his Obſcurity; his Language (ſaith <hi>Photius</hi>) is Elevated, Copious, and Artificial, but without Labour; he hath diſcover'd the <hi>Arcana Imperii,</hi> Election of their Magiſtrates, <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Rites and Ceremones, the <hi>Apotheſis</hi> and Conſecration of their departed Emperours, together with the Ceremony of <hi>Auguſt</hi>'s Funeral, <hi>Livia</hi>'s Mourning, and the letting flye the Eagle from the Funeral Pile, better than any other <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> either before, or ſince.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:53633:44"/>Nevertheleſs he is condemn'd for his tedious ſuperfluity of Orations; for too much adhering to <hi>Caeſar</hi> againſt <hi>Pompey</hi> in complyance with the Times; for impartially ſiding with <hi>Antonius,</hi> and beſpattering <hi>Cicero;</hi> for too much Superſtition and Credulity given to <hi>Veſpaſian</hi>'s Cure, and <hi>Appollonius Tyanaeus</hi> his Prediction; as well as for his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies againſt <hi>Seneca,</hi> unleſs his ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>breviator <hi>Tigellinus</hi> miſquotes him. But I ſhall not accuſe him (as <hi>Barro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> does,) for attributing the Victories of <hi>Marcus Aurelius</hi> rather to the Magick of the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerer <hi>Arnaphis,</hi> than the Prayers of the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> becauſe he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was an <hi>Heathen.</hi> Laſtly, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his Hiſtory, <hi>Suidas</hi> and <hi>Vola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terranus</hi> (how true I know not) make him the Author of <hi>Arrianus</hi> the <hi>Phyloſophers</hi> Life, the Actions of <hi>Trajan,</hi> certain <hi>Itineraries,</hi> three Books <hi>de Principe,</hi> and ſome ſmall Tracts of <hi>Morality.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:53633:44"/>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Herodian?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Herodian,</hi> the Son of <hi>Apol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonius Difficilis,</hi> was originally a <hi>Grammarian</hi> of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> and liv'd in the third <hi>Century</hi> under <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modus</hi> the Emperour. He wrote Eight Books of <hi>Hiſtory</hi> of his own time, beginning with the Death of <hi>Marcus Aurelius Antoninus</hi> the <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> and ending with the Murder of the two Emperors, <hi>Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binus</hi> and <hi>Puppienus.</hi> His <hi>Hiſtory</hi> comprehends the ſpace of 70 years, and is prais'd, not only by <hi>Photius</hi> for his Elegant Stile, but alſo by <hi>Julius Capitolinus, Tribonius Pollio, Ammianus Marcellinus,</hi> and <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanus,</hi> for the Fidelity of his <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Accounts, wherein (according to his <hi>Latin</hi> Interpreter <hi>Angelus Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litianus</hi>) he only ſwerves in his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Maximus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He imitates <hi>Dion Caſſius</hi> in his Relation of the Ceremonies uſed
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:53633:45"/>
at the <hi>Apotheoſis</hi> of the <hi>Roman</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors, particularly of <hi>Severus</hi> his Funeral Rites, in the beginning of his fourth Book. As for the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurers upon <hi>Herodian,</hi> he is thought by ſome to be too full of Orations; as alſo, to be too ſevere upon the Empreſs <hi>Mammea,</hi> out of ill will to her Son <hi>Alexander Severus,</hi> to whom he was a declar'd Enemy. <hi>Suidas</hi> ſaith that <hi>Herodian</hi> wrote many other Pieces, the which (if he did) are now loſt.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Eunapius?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Eunapius Sardianus</hi> liv'd in the times of <hi>Valentinian, Valens</hi> and <hi>Gratian:</hi> He is called <hi>Sardianus</hi> from <hi>Sardis</hi> a City in <hi>Lydia,</hi> the place of his Birth, from whence he travelled to <hi>Athens,</hi> and there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came eminent, as well for <hi>Sophiſtry</hi> and <hi>Phyſick,</hi> as <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> being the Diſciple of the Great <hi>Proaeteſius,</hi> and nearly related to the Noble
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:53633:45"/>
Sophiſt <hi>Chryſanthius,</hi> who married <hi>Eunapius</hi> his Siſters Daughter. At the perſwaſion of this <hi>Chryſanthius,</hi> he wrote an elegant piece of the Lives of the <hi>Sophiſts,</hi> and afterwards that other Hiſtorical Tract of the <hi>Roman</hi> Emperours, beginning where <hi>Hero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dian</hi> left off, and ſo continuing it to his own times.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Photius</hi> praiſes his Stile, but con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demns his Hiſtory, for traducing <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, and extol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Julian,</hi> as alſo (in his Lives of the <hi>Sophiſts</hi>) for being too ſevere upon the <hi>Chriſtians.</hi> Laſtly, beſides theſe two pieces here mention'd, we have likewiſe a fragment of another Treatiſe of <hi>Eunapius,</hi> Entituled, <hi>de Legationibus,</hi> which was firſt pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh'd by <hi>Andrea Shottus,</hi> and is now annexed to the <hi>Byzantine</hi> Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Zoſimus?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:53633:46"/>
               <hi>Anſ. Zoſimus</hi> liv'd in the time of <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the younger, and wrote ſix Books of <hi>History;</hi> whereof the firſt doth briefly deſcribe all the Emperours from <hi>Auguſtus</hi> to <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> and ſo on to <hi>Diocleſian:</hi> But the other five Books (which extends to the Siege of <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Alaricus</hi>) are more copious and large, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally when he treats of the grounds of the Diviſion betwixt <hi>Arcadius</hi> and <hi>Honorius,</hi> whereof he himſelf was an Eye-witneſs.</p>
            <p>This Hiſtory of <hi>Zoſimus</hi> is ſaid to be a meer Abridgement of <hi>Euna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius;</hi> except in thoſe paſſages where he praiſes <hi>Stilico,</hi> whom <hi>Ennapius</hi> condemns. <hi>Evagrius, Photius</hi> and others ſay, that he barks like a Dog at the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> and unworthily traduces <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great: As alſo, that he not only irreligiouſly beſpatters <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> but Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitiouſly adhers to <hi>Paganiſm,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing over-credulous in ſundry of the
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:53633:46"/>
               <hi>Heathen</hi> Miracles. However, <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unclavius,</hi> who firſt Tranſlated <hi>Zo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſimus</hi> into <hi>Latin,</hi> makes great Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logies, as well for his inveighing againſt the <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſince <hi>Zoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus</hi> himſelf was an <hi>Heathen,</hi> as for his Traducing <hi>Conſtantine,</hi> ſince he diſcovers as well his Vices. Laſtly, <hi>Photius</hi> applauds the Purity of his Stile, the Brevity of his Sentences, and Conciſeneſs of his Phraſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing exempt from Figures or long Orations.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Euſebius?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Euſebius Pamphili</hi> (ſo cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from the Intimacy betwixt him and the Martyr <hi>Pamphilius,</hi>) was Biſhop of <hi>Caeſarea,</hi> the chief Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan of all the Churches in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtine,</hi> and moſt Ancient of all the Eccleſiaſtical Writers in the fourth <hi>Century. For</hi> (as St. <hi>Jerome</hi> in his Life tells us) Euſebius <hi>flouriſh'd un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> Conſtantine <hi>the Great, and his
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:53633:47"/>
Son</hi> Conſtantius: So that (perhaps) fear might oblige him to render a more favourable account of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine,</hi> than <hi>Zoſimus</hi> did. As for his Writings, they are various, both Prophane and Sacred: The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, is his <hi>Chronicle</hi> from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the World to <hi>Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines</hi> twentieth year, which was, 326 years after Chriſt; <hi>Joſeph Sca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liger</hi> eſteems this Piece to be only a Tranſcript out of <hi>Julius Africanus.</hi> As for the Sacred Writings of <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius,</hi> they were theſe: <hi>Of Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical Preparation,</hi> fifteen Books; <hi>Of Evangelical Demonſtration,</hi> twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Books, whereof but ten are now extant; <hi>Of Divine Apparitions,</hi> five Books; <hi>Of Eccleſiaſtical Hiſtory,</hi> ten Books; <hi>Of the Diſagreement of the</hi> Evangeliſts; <hi>upon the Prophet</hi> Eſay, ten Books; <hi>Againſt Porphyrie,</hi> thirty Books, whereof twenty were only known to St. <hi>Jerome; Of Topicks,</hi> one Book; <hi>A Defence
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:53633:47"/>
of</hi> Origen, in ſix Books; <hi>The Life of</hi> Pamphilius, in three Books, and ſeveral other Books of Martyrs; <hi>Learned Commentaries on the whole Book of</hi> Pſalms; <hi>The Life of</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantine, in, four Books, <hi>Againſt</hi> Hierooles, Eight Books; <hi>Againſt Fatal Deſtiny,</hi> one Book; and three Books againſt <hi>Marcellus,</hi> mention'd by <hi>Socrates,</hi> lib. 2. <hi>Eccleſt. Hiſt.</hi> All which ſeveral Pieces have been Tranſlated by ſeveral hands. In his <hi>Evangelical Demonſtration,</hi> he ſeems to favour <hi>Arrianiſm,</hi> notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding his Subſcription to the <hi>Nicene-Council,</hi> and therefore is to be read with Caution.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Procopius?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Procopius was born at <hi>Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaria</hi> in <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> from whence he went to <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> in the time of the Emperour <hi>Anastatius,</hi> by whom he was highly eſteem'd, as alſo by <hi>Juſtin</hi> the firſt; and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:53633:48"/>
by <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> ſo as to be preferr'd to the Senate with the Quality of <hi>Illustrious,</hi> and created <hi>Praefect</hi> of New <hi>Rome:</hi> Beſides which, he was chief Secretary to the General <hi>Beliſarius</hi> in all the Wars of <hi>Perſia, Africk</hi> and <hi>Italy;</hi> which makes him every where give ſo Honourable a Character of him. <hi>Procopius</hi> was both an <hi>Orator, So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phister, Rhetorician</hi> and <hi>Hiſtorian.</hi> His Hiſtory conſiſts of eight Books, whereof, the firſt two comprehend the <hi>Perſian</hi> War, Abbreviated by <hi>Photius:</hi> The two next the <hi>Vandal</hi> Wars: and the four laſt, the War with the <hi>Goths:</hi> Of all which, there is a <hi>Compendium</hi> in the <hi>Preface</hi> of <hi>Agathias,</hi> who began his <hi>Hiſtory</hi> where <hi>Procopius</hi> ended. His ninth Book called <hi>Anecdota,</hi> or the <hi>Secret History of</hi> Juſtinian, which is a Scur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous Invective againſt that Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour and his Wife <hi>Theodora,</hi> though mention'd in <hi>Suidas,</hi> was thought
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:53633:48"/>
by <hi>Voſſius</hi> to have been loſt, but has ſince been made publick by <hi>Heſchae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> and others. Now beſides the fore-mention'd Pieces, there is ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Treatiſe <hi>de Aedificiis</hi> in ſix Books, which <hi>Procopius</hi> wrote for the Honour of <hi>Juſtinians</hi> Buildings in which Diſcourſe there are ſome paſſes that make many eſteem our Author a <hi>Christian,</hi> but if his whole works are examin'd, he will be found no better than a Superſtitious <hi>Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick</hi> Writer. <hi>Procopius</hi> is extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly condemn'd, not only for his too ſevere reproach of the <hi>French;</hi> but likewiſe, for his <hi>Anecdota</hi> or Libel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Invective againſt the Emperour and Empreſs, <hi>Juſtinian</hi> and <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dora:</hi> Which not only varies from it in Stile, but alſo in Matter contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicts all his other Works, wherein he ever mentions the Emperour and Empreſs with great Honour and Applauſe; Inſomuch that for this very reaſon many have doubted
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:53633:49"/>
whether that Piece is not Spurious, and written by ſome other hand. Laſtly, by his Oblique Orations he attempts to imitate the Ancients, but comes far ſhort of them. His Tranſlator <hi>Porſona,</hi> did rather per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert, than convert him</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Agathias?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Agathias</hi> (the Son of <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nonius</hi>) was born at <hi>Murina</hi> a City of <hi>Aſia,</hi> in the Reign of <hi>Juſtinian;</hi> he profeſſed the Law, and pleaded as an Advocate at <hi>Smyrna,</hi> for which reaſon he was Sir-named <hi>Scholasticus.</hi> His firſt ſtudy was Poetry, which made him publiſh many ſmall Poems in Heroick Verſe under the Title of <hi>Daphnicks,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with divers Epigrams; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by being prepar'd with a Stile moſt agreeable florid, he (by the advice of <hi>Eutychianus</hi> prime Secretary of State) undertook to write an Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry concerning the <hi>Empire</hi> and Deeds of
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:53633:49"/>
               <hi>Justinian</hi> in five Books, beginning where <hi>Procopius</hi> left off; which Piece he finiſh'd in the Reign of <hi>Justin</hi> the ſecond, as he himſelf de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clares in his Preface. Now albeit <hi>Agathias</hi> highly extols <hi>Procopius,</hi> yet he differs from him in many things, particularly in his commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the <hi>French,</hi> whom <hi>Procopius</hi> decryes. He likewiſe (though an <hi>Heathen,</hi> as appears by his Diſcourſe of <hi>Stephen</hi> the <hi>Proto-martyr,</hi>) ſeems to ſpeak more favourably of the <hi>Christians</hi> in the beginning of his <hi>History,</hi> where he praiſes the <hi>French</hi> for being ſo. Finally, his account of the <hi>Oriental</hi> Monarchys, in the end of his ſecond Book, as well as his Succeſſion of the <hi>Perſian</hi> Kings after <hi>Artaxerxes,</hi> in his fourth Book, are rendred very conſiderable by the aſſiſtance of his Interpreter <hi>Sergius,</hi> who was furniſh'd herein, by the Notaries and Library-keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of all the Kings and publick Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chives in <hi>Perſia,</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="5" type="book">
            <pb n="82" facs="tcp:53633:50"/>
            <head>
               <hi>LIB.</hi> V. OF THE ANCIENT LATINE HISTORIANS.</head>
            <p>Qu. <hi>WHich are the most emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent of the Ancient</hi> La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin <hi>Hiſtorians?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Julius Caeſar, Saluſt, Livy, Paterculus, Valerius Maximus, Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Curtius, Tacitus, Florus, Suetoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Juſtin,</hi> and <hi>Marcelinus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Caeſar?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Cajus Julius Caeſar</hi> (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from the Noble <hi>Julian</hi> Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily) was the firſt Founder of the <hi>Roman</hi> Empire; yet no leſs emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:53633:50"/>
for his <hi>Commentaries,</hi> than his <hi>Conqueſts:</hi> Uſing his Pen with the ſame Vigour, as he us'd his Sword; in ſo much, that, as <hi>Quintilian</hi> ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves, he was the only <hi>Roman,</hi> who for Eloquence might have been op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to <hi>Cicero:</hi> And who, as <hi>Gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raldus</hi> ſaith) did alone overcome all others both in Writing and Fight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. In his tender years he addicted himſelf to Poetry, and Compos'd the Tragedy of <hi>Oedipus,</hi> the Praiſe of <hi>Hercules,</hi> and ſeveral other Poems under the Title of <hi>Julii,</hi> which <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus</hi> afterwards prohibited to be publiſh'd. Neither was he leſs fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for his Skill in Oratory, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs his <hi>Funeral Orations</hi> on his Wife <hi>Cornelia,</hi> and Aunt <hi>Julia,</hi> his Accuſation of <hi>Dolabella,</hi> his Invectives againſt <hi>Cato,</hi> and his Orations for the <hi>Bythinian</hi> Law <hi>Plautia,</hi> for <hi>Decius</hi> the <hi>Samnite,</hi> for <hi>Sextilius</hi> and others, Likewiſe his two Books of <hi>Analogy</hi> gave him
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:53633:51"/>
great repute among the <hi>Gramma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians.</hi> Beſides which, he wrote ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral other Tracts of <hi>Augurie,</hi> and witty <hi>Apothegms;</hi> as well as of the motion of the <hi>Stares,</hi> which he had Learnt in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and wherein he Prognoſticated his own Death, on the <hi>Ides</hi> of <hi>March,</hi> as the Elder <hi>Pliny</hi> relates; nor is he leſs eminent for his Reformation of the <hi>Kalen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der.</hi> But what ſurpaſſed all his other Writings, were his ſeven Books of <hi>Commentaries,</hi> deſcribing nothing but his own Actions, and things that he himſelf had ſeen. <hi>Aſinius Pollio,</hi> (that carping Critick) accuſes him (as <hi>Suetonius</hi> ſaith) for ſuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving from the Truth in many Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations about himſelf, and that he differs extreamly from the account which <hi>Dion, Plutarch</hi> and other Authors give of the ſame Actions; as alſo, that he reports many things unjuſtly to the Defamation of the Ancient <hi>Gauls:</hi> But theſe Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:53633:51"/>
are only conjectural. As for the excellency of his Stile, 'tis ſo Eaſie, Natural and Eloquent, that his <hi>Latin</hi> has ever been compar'd to <hi>Xenophon</hi>'s <hi>Greek,</hi> as well as his other Characters. The eight Book of his <hi>Commentaries</hi> was written by <hi>Hirtius. Caeſars</hi> Writings, though adorn'd with ſome Orations, are deſtitute of many <hi>Rhetorical</hi> Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, wherewith he could have beautified them; in ſo much, that <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero</hi> eſteems his <hi>Commentaries</hi> to be nothing but ſhort Notes prepared by <hi>Caeſar</hi> in order to a more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat Hiſtory, had not his untimely Murder prevented him.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſt?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Criſpus Saluſtius,</hi> or, as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers call him, <hi>Salluſtius,</hi> was born at <hi>Amiternum</hi> in the <hi>Sabines</hi> Terri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory, the third year of the 173<hi rend="sup">d.</hi> 
               <hi>Olympiad,</hi> which was the ſame year that <hi>Sylla</hi>'s Souldiers took and
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:53633:52"/>
Sack'd <hi>Athens;</hi> for he was Elder than <hi>Caeſar,</hi> though he out-liv'd him ſeven years, <hi>Saluſt</hi> was firſt Educated in <hi>Rome,</hi> ſpending his youth in Ingenious Studies, ſo as to be preferr'd to many conſiderable Offices in the Government: as, <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nator, Tribune, Treaſurer,</hi> and <hi>Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tour</hi> in <hi>Africk</hi> by the favour of <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius Caeſar,</hi> in which laſt Office, by his Extortions, he grew ſo vaſtly Rich, as to purchaſe the Village <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burte,</hi> and his Country-houſe at <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voli,</hi> as well as the chief Houſes on <hi>Mount Quirinal</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> together with thoſe ſpacious Gardens, called (at this day) <hi>The Gardens of</hi> Saluſt. He was deſcended from the Noble <hi>Saluſtian</hi> Family; and Educated un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Tutor <hi>Attejus Praetextatus Philologus.</hi> Of his Works, <hi>Catalin</hi>'s <hi>Conſpiracy,</hi> and the <hi>Jugurthine</hi> War, are the two chief, that are extant; Beſides which, he wrote the Hiſtory of <hi>Rome</hi> from its foundation, with
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:53633:52"/>
a particular Narration of <hi>Marius</hi> and <hi>Sylla,</hi> as alſo the Atchievments of <hi>Pompey</hi> in the <hi>Mithridatick</hi> War, of all which, we have only ſome few Fragments remain; but for the true delivery of his <hi>Punick</hi> Hiſtory, he was ſo Zealous, that he Travail'd into <hi>Africa</hi> on purpoſe, to be the better inform'd. His Stile, in imita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Thucydides,</hi> whom <hi>Quintili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an</hi> compares him to,) is Conciſe, Short, and Pithy. Of the Ancients, as well as <hi>Tacitus,</hi> and <hi>Seneca,</hi> as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> did highly eſteem <hi>Saluſt;</hi> and of the modern Criticks, <hi>Lip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius, Turnebus</hi> and <hi>Scaliger</hi> prefer him to <hi>Caeſar</hi> or <hi>Livy.</hi> Nevertheleſs, <hi>Aſinius Pollio, Livy</hi> and others ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him for inventing new words, as well as for the uſing obſolete ones; and for too much obſcure brevity in his expreſſions, wherein <hi>Tacitus</hi> imitates him. He is likewiſe cenſur'd for ſtealing out of <hi>Thucy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cides</hi> and <hi>Cato</hi> many Select Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:53633:53"/>
and for the too often repetition of the ſame words; as well as for inſerting many ineſſential things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his Hiſtory, more eſpecially his two Prefaces before <hi>Catalin</hi>'s <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracy,</hi> and the <hi>Jugurthine</hi> War, which relate not at all to the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſubjects: But the firſt a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Harangue againſt Idleneſs; and the ſecond an Invective againſt thoſe whom Debauchery diverted from their Employs. Yet that, for the which he was the moſt condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, is his own extravagant Life, ſo much contrary to his Writings: When, not being ſatisfied with his own Wife <hi>Terentia,</hi> whom he mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried after her Divorce from <hi>Cicero,</hi> he was taken in Adultery with <hi>Fauſta, Lucius Sylla</hi>'s Daughter; for the which he was not only ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd the Senate, but condemn'd alſo to be Whipt by <hi>Milo,</hi> and fain to buy off that puniſhment with Money. Finally, his Orations diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:53633:53"/>
both his amity to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and enmity to <hi>Cicero.</hi> Notwithſtanding ſome queſtion, whether theſe two addreſs'd to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> were <hi>Saluſts</hi> or no. But moſt certain it is, that that one Oration which <hi>Cicero</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribes to <hi>Saluſt</hi> is counterfeit, and none of his, it being in no wiſe Hiſtorical. The moſt conſiderable of his Friends were, <hi>Julius Caeſar, Cornelius Nepos, Meſſala,</hi> and <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gidius Figulus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Livy?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Titus Livius Patavinus,</hi> was born at <hi>Padua,</hi> and flouriſh'd chiefly under <hi>Auguſtus</hi> and <hi>Tiberius.</hi> He be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to write after <hi>Auguſtus</hi>'s Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph for the War at <hi>Actium,</hi> and finiſhed his Hiſtory in the beginning of <hi>Tiberius</hi>'s reign. He wrote (as <hi>Seneca</hi> tells us, many <hi>Philoſophical Dialogues</hi> before he came to <hi>Rome,</hi> the which he dedicated to <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> whereby he procured his
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:53633:54"/>
Favour. And <hi>Quintinian</hi> informs us, that in a Letter to his Son, he deliver'd many excellent Precepts of <hi>Rhetorick;</hi> but his chief Piece is his Hiſtory, which contain'd 142 Books, or (as ſome ſay) but 140. beginning with the Foundation of <hi>Rome</hi> by <hi>Romulus,</hi> and extending for the ſpace of 746 years, to the <hi>German</hi> War, mannag'd by <hi>Druſus.</hi> who loſt his Life in that Expedition. This Hiſtory was not divided into <hi>Decades</hi> (as now we find it,) by <hi>Livy</hi> himſelf, but by others ſince his time. And of the 140, or 142 Books which he wrote, there re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main at preſent not above 35. nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther are thoſe altogether entire: For that the whole ſecond <hi>Decade</hi> is wanting; alſo we have but the firſt, third and fourth, with half of the fifth, which was found at <hi>Wormes,</hi> by one <hi>Symon Gryneus.</hi> Likewiſe the beginning of the fourty third Book has been lately recover'd by a
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:53633:54"/>
               <hi>Manuſcript</hi> in the Chapter of <hi>Bam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg.</hi> But for the remaining four<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen <hi>Decades,</hi> we muſt reſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with the Epitomy of <hi>Florus,</hi> who, as ſome vainly fancy, was the occaſion of the loſs of the whole. His Stile, notwithſtanding <hi>Aſinius Pollio</hi> blames it for its Patavinity, or <hi>Paduan</hi> Dialect, (where he writes <hi>ſibe</hi> for <hi>ſibi,</hi> and <hi>quaſe</hi> for <hi>quaſi,</hi> as we now pronounce it;) is yet extoll'd by <hi>Quintilian,</hi> as moſt Eloquent, and his Hiſtory equall'd to <hi>Herodotus.</hi> Alſo, however the Emperour <hi>Caligula</hi> accuſes him of Verboſity, yet the ſame Prince was no leſs an enemy to <hi>Homer, Virgil, Seneca,</hi> and all Ingenious men. It is true, that <hi>Auguſtus</hi> blamed <hi>Livy</hi> for too much favouring <hi>Pompey</hi>'s party againſt <hi>Caeſar,</hi> but yet he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drew not his favor from him, as per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving it his Countries cauſe, who were all of the <hi>Pompejan</hi> Faction. Again, <hi>Trogus Pompejus</hi> (as <hi>Juſtin</hi>
               <pb n="92" facs="tcp:53633:55"/>
informs us) accuſes <hi>Livy</hi>'s Orations, as too direct and long, which cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure might happily, ariſe out of Jealouſy betwixt two <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> of the ſame Age and Subject. And for what <hi>Maſcardi</hi> blames him, of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning his Hiſtory with part of an <hi>Hexameter</hi> Verſe, 'tis frivolous, ſince there is no Proſe without ſomething of the like nature occuring. <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neca</hi> more juſtly accuſes him of en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy to <hi>Saluſt,</hi> in preferring <hi>Thucydi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des</hi> ſo much above him; but yet <hi>Seneca</hi> terms him the moſt Eloquent. Finally, the Aſperſion which can with moſt difficulty be wip'd off from <hi>Livy,</hi> is that, for the which <hi>Gregory</hi> the Great prohibited him to be kept in any Chriſtian Library, and which <hi>Cauſabon</hi> mentions in his Preface to <hi>Polybius,</hi> viz. his noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Credulity in the <hi>Pagan</hi> Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition, where he fills his Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with <hi>Prodigies;</hi> as, of an <hi>Oxes</hi> Speaking; a <hi>Mules</hi> Engendring,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:53633:55"/>
the Metamorphoſis of Men, Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and other Creatures; ſhowres of Flint-ſtones, Milk, Blood, Fleſh and Chalk; the Statues of Gods Weeping, Speaking, and ſhedding Tears of Blood, Armies engaging in the Air, and Ghoſts appearing; together with Lakes and Rivers of Blood: All which nevertheleſs he repreſents only as the fond opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of others, and not to be cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dited.</p>
            <p>Laſt of all, <hi>Gruterus</hi> entitles him the Prince of <hi>Latine</hi> Hiſtory, <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thius,</hi> the <hi>Patavinian Syren,</hi> and <hi>Lipſius,</hi> the moſt <hi>Plentiful of Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorians,</hi> wherein (as he obſerves) we meet with things too good for us. He died in the fourth year of <hi>Tiberius.</hi> He was choſen by the Senate to be Tutor to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Claudius</hi> in his youth. And (as <hi>Pliny</hi> the younger tells us) <hi>One travelled to</hi> Rome <hi>from the remoteſt parts of</hi> Spain, <hi>only to have a ſight of</hi> Livy.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="94" facs="tcp:53633:56"/>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Vellejus Paterculus?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Vellejus Paterculus</hi> (deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from the Ancient War-like Princes of <hi>Campaigne</hi>) was at firſt a Military Tribune in <hi>France,</hi> then Praefect of Horſes in <hi>Germany,</hi> after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards Quaeſtor, and laſt of all <hi>Tibe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rius</hi>'s Legate in the <hi>Pannonian</hi> War; as he himſelf informs us. About the 16th. year of <hi>Tiberius</hi> he compoſed his <hi>Epitomy of</hi> Roman <hi>Hiſtory</hi> in two Books, whereof the beginning of the firſt is loſt. He pretends to begin only with the Foundation of <hi>Rome,</hi> nevertheleſs, as appears by the remains of his firſt Book, He treats of things far more Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, and ſo comes down to his own time, the 16th. year of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> which was the 32d. year after the Birth of Chriſt. <hi>Voſſius, Lipſius</hi> and others extol the Elegancy of his Stile, and allow him to have given us a Judicious account of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:53633:56"/>
ſome things which are not elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where to be met with. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, he is condemned for too much flattering the Houſe of <hi>Augustus,</hi> as well as for paraſitically applau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding even the Extravagancies of <hi>Tiberius</hi> and his Evil Councellor <hi>Sejanus,</hi> whom he magnifies for the moſt Vertuous of men. But, to conclude, his greateſt Excellency is his Eloquence, which appears chiefly in his Invectives and Enco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miums, as where he traduces <hi>Mark Anthony,</hi> and extols <hi>Cicero.</hi> Some attribute this Author another Frag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the defeat of the <hi>Roman</hi> Legion by the <hi>Griſons,</hi> the which <hi>Voſſius, Velſerus,</hi> and other Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Criticks have demonſtrated to be a counterfeit.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Valerius Maximus?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Valerius Maximus,</hi> a <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Citizen of a Noble <hi>Patrician</hi> Family, derived his Pedegree from
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:53633:57"/>
the <hi>Valerian</hi> Family by his Fathers ſide, and from the <hi>Fabians</hi> by his Mother. In his youth he was ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiated in Learning, but coming to be of Age, he ſerved for ſome time in the Wars, and Sailed with <hi>Sex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Pompejus</hi> into <hi>Aſia:</hi> From whence, being returned to <hi>Rome,</hi> he publiſhed in nine Books his va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Hiſtory, or rather Miſcellani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous collection of memorable Deeds and Sayings that had occurred a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Romans;</hi> the which he wrote at the latter end of <hi>Tiberius</hi> his reign, and after the diſgrace of <hi>Sejanus,</hi> which makes him ſo boldly traduce that Favourite, whom <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terculus</hi> was obliged to flatter, as writing in the time of his Proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity. Finally, he is condemn'd for the obſcurity and unpoliteneſs of Stile.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Quintus Curtius?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="97" facs="tcp:53633:57"/>
               <hi>Anſ. Quintus Curtius Rufus,</hi> though born (as moſt think) in the Reign of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> yet, living to a great Age, flouriſhed chiefly under <hi>Veſpaſian:</hi> And was the ſame <hi>Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> whom <hi>Suetonius</hi> makes in his younger days to teach <hi>Rhetorick</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der <hi>Tiberius;</hi> as alſo the ſame, to whom (as the younger <hi>Pliny</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports,) a Phantaſme appear'd in <hi>Africa.</hi> He wrote the Life and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pliots of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great in ten Books; whereof, the two firſt, and end of the fifth are loſt, as alſo the beginning of the ſixth; and in ſome parts of his tenth or laſt Book, there appears a defect: Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, <hi>Chriſtopher Bruno</hi> has ſupplyed the two firſt Books out of <hi>Arrianus, Juſtin</hi> and <hi>Diodorus.</hi> As for the Cenſures that paſs upon him, <hi>Gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, Maſcardi</hi> and others condemn him for an ill Geographer, in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the <hi>River Ganges</hi> run from the <hi>South,</hi> and confounding Mount
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:53633:58"/>
               <hi>Taurus</hi> with <hi>Caucaſus,</hi> as alſo miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the <hi>Jaxartes</hi> of <hi>Pliny</hi> for the <hi>River Tanais:</hi> Likewiſe for too much abounding in Sentences, and making perſons ſpeak improper to the Characters they bear, as in the Oration of the <hi>Scythians</hi> to <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander,</hi> in his ſeventh Book. But all theſe accuſations are frivolous and groundleſs, in compariſon of that which is urged againſt him, for vindicating the Brutiſh and Unna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Luſt of <hi>Alexander</hi> to the Eunuch <hi>Bagoas,</hi> which <hi>Curtius</hi> juſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies as Lawful. Nevertheleſs, he is as much eſteem'd of among the Cri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks, as any of the <hi>Latine Hiſtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> both for ſincerity and Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and Eloquence. <hi>Lipſius</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers him before all others for the peruſal of Princes. <hi>Voſſius</hi> ſaith, <hi>He is more Elegant, than Perſpicuous;</hi> yet allows his Words to be Choice, his Sentences Accute, his Orations Eloquent, and his Phraſe worthy of
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:53633:58"/>
               <hi>Auguſtus</hi>'s Age. As for his Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, whether direct or oblique, they are all Excellent. Neither is he impertinent in Digreſſions, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs you will accuſe his Deſcription of <hi>India</hi> for one, which was really eſſential to his Deſign. Laſtly, <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonſus</hi> King of <hi>Arragon</hi> was reco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered from a dangerous fit of Sick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs by the diverſion he took in the reading of this Author, which made him cry out, <hi>That he owed his Recovery neither to</hi> Hippocrates <hi>nor</hi> Avicenne, <hi>but only to</hi> Quintus Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Cornelius Tacitus,</hi> Praefect of the <hi>Belgick Gauls</hi> under the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour <hi>Adrian,</hi> beſides his <hi>Annals,</hi> (which reach from the Scene of <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> to the end of <hi>Nero</hi>'s Reign, excepting his laſt twelve years,) wrote alſo an Hiſtory, that extends from the Death of <hi>Nero,</hi>
               <pb n="100" facs="tcp:53633:59"/>
to the Government of <hi>Nerva</hi> and <hi>Trajan;</hi> of which Hiſtory, there are now extant but Five Books: And <hi>Lipſius,</hi> with reaſon, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jectures, that there are at leaſt Ten more loſt, in as much as they were all ſaid to reach from <hi>Galba</hi> to <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jan,</hi> which was the ſpace of one and twenty years; whereof the five we have now left us, treat but of one whole year. His Hiſtory is quoted in the eleventh of his <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals,</hi> whence we may conclude That to have been firſt written. Now, beſides his <hi>Annals</hi> and <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory,</hi> he wrote alſo a Treatiſe of <hi>Germany</hi> and its Inhabitants, with another Book of the Life of his Father in Law <hi>Agricola:</hi> Both which pieces are now extant. But for the other Tract of the corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Roman</hi> Eloquence, which ſome attribute to <hi>Tacitus,</hi> and others to <hi>Quintilian,</hi> 'tis thought by <hi>Lip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſius</hi> and other Learned men to have
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:53633:59"/>
been written by neither. Now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong theſe many Judicious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons who extol this Author, <hi>Voſſius</hi> (though he prefers the Eloquence of his <hi>Hiſtory</hi> before that of his <hi>Annals,</hi>) yet allows him to be every where <hi>Grave and Elegant:</hi> Alſo <hi>Lipſius</hi> calls him, <hi>a ſharp and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Writer, and Imitator of</hi> Saluſt: <hi>Sidonius</hi> would have him never mention'd without <hi>Praiſe:</hi> But the Emperour <hi>Tacitus</hi> had ſo great a veneration for his Anceſtor and Name-ſake, that he made his Books be tranſcrib'd no leſs then ten times in one year, and cauſed his Statue to be erected in all publick Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. Notwithſtanding, he hath not been totally exempt from Cenſure: For <hi>Alciatus,</hi> rather out of Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than Reaſon, preferr'd his Friend <hi>Paulus Jovius</hi> before him; and <hi>Ferret,</hi> as well out of Igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, as Vanity, accuſes <hi>Tacitus</hi> of writing ill <hi>Latine;</hi> However
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:53633:60"/>
               <hi>Pliny</hi> the younger, magnifies his Eloquence therein. Alſo <hi>Vopiſcus</hi> (only to juſtify his Aſſertion, that all Narrations are mixt with un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truths,) accuſes <hi>Tacitus</hi> of delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring falſities, but gives no inſtance where. Likewiſe, <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> and <hi>Tertullian</hi> bribed rather with Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, than Judgment, accuſe <hi>Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citus</hi> as an Impoſture, for that he derides the Chriſtians, abuſes the Miracles of <hi>Moſes,</hi> and upbraids the <hi>Jews</hi> for their adoring the Effigies of an Aſs, in the fifth Book of his <hi>Hiſtory:</hi> Which, as coming from an <hi>Heathen,</hi> is not altogether ſo criminal; but rather to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn'd for a digreſſion, than for an Impiety. Finally, he equals as well <hi>Thucydides,</hi> as <hi>Saluſt,</hi> in the number of his choice Sentences; out of which, the wiſeſt Politicians have ſelected their moſt prudent Maxims of State.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="103" facs="tcp:53633:60"/>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Lucius Florus?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Lucius Annaeus Florus</hi> (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from the Noble <hi>Annaean</hi> Family, and thereby allayed to the <hi>Senececaes</hi>) lived under the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Adrian;</hi> and compoſed an Epitomy of <hi>Roman Hiſtory</hi> in four Books. Some queſtion whether he was the ſame Author that annex'd the Arguments to <hi>Livy</hi>'s <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> but 'tis a great errour to imagine, that he ever deſign'd the Epitomy of all <hi>Livy</hi>'s works, much leſs, that he ſhould occaſion the loſs of any part of them. His ſtile is Poetical, uſing (like <hi>Virgil</hi>) Hemeſticks in his Periods, and writes more like a <hi>Declamer</hi> than a <hi>Hiſtorian,</hi> which makes <hi>Sigonius</hi> brand him for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent. His account of the <hi>Suns</hi> being ſeen to fall into the <hi>Ocean,</hi> and there heard with Horrour to extinguiſh its Beams in the Waves; (as mention'd in his Deſcription of
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:53633:61"/>
               <hi>Brutus</hi> his Sea Voyage,) alſo his Report of two Spirits in the ſhape of young men appearing in <hi>Rome</hi> near the Temple of <hi>Caſtor</hi> and <hi>Pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lux;</hi> (when he ſpeaks of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feat of <hi>Cimbri</hi> by <hi>Marius;</hi>) are things altogether incredible, and not fit to be inſerted in <hi>Hiſtory;</hi> as <hi>Scaliger,</hi> in his Comment on <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius,</hi> well obſerves. Yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, <hi>Voſſius</hi> allows him to be a Writer, that is both Elegant and Eloquent, and (except in ſome few places) truly Florid.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Suetonius?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Caius Suetonius Tranquillus</hi> (whoſe Fathers name was <hi>Suetonius Lenis,</hi> as he himſelf teſtifies in the Life of <hi>Otho,</hi>) was Secretary of State to the Emperour <hi>Adrian,</hi> till being ſuſpected of too great Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liarity with the Empreſs <hi>Sabina,</hi> he was removed from that Employ. After which, he apply'd himſelf to
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:53633:61"/>
writing, and compos'd theſe ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Pices: To wit, <hi>The Lives of the Twelve firſt</hi> Roman <hi>Emperours,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning with <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding with the death of <hi>Domitian,</hi> in the 98th. year of Chriſt, which piece is now extant: Together with other Tracts of the Illuſtrious <hi>Grammarians, Rhetoricians,</hi> and <hi>Poets,</hi> whereof at this day, only ſome Fragments remain; Beſides, <hi>a Diſcourſe of the</hi> Roman <hi>Games,</hi> a piece call'd, <hi>the Republick of</hi> Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cero, <hi>and of the moſt Illustrious Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies of</hi> Rome, all which are pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh'd in the ruines of time. <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonius</hi> likewiſe tells us of another Book of Kings divided into three parts, <hi>Which</hi> (he ſaith) <hi>was written by</hi> Suetonius, <hi>and afterwards con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted into a Poem by</hi> Pontius Pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linus. But for that Treatiſe of the Life of the Elder <hi>Pliny,</hi> which goes under the Name of <hi>Suetonius,</hi> it was certainly none of his; for the
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:53633:62"/>
great Intimacy betwixt our Author and the younger <hi>Pliny,</hi> would have produced a more Honourable Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of his Friends Uncle, the Elder <hi>Pliny,</hi> than is there to be found, had <hi>Suetonius</hi> been the Writer of it. Some are of opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that the beginning of his firſt Book of the twelve <hi>Caeſars</hi> is wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, becauſe there is no mention of the Birth and firſt years of <hi>Julius Caeſar,</hi> as there is of the Original and Education of all the other Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, in the reſt of their Lives As for the Cenſures that are paſſed upon <hi>Suetonius,</hi> they are chiefly two; the firſt, <hi>For his exclaiming against the turbulent Superſtition of the</hi> Chriſtians; And the ſecond, <hi>for his Deſcription of Vice in the Lives of</hi> Tiberius, Nero, <hi>and</hi> Caligula; whereof, if you will pardon him the firſt as an <hi>Heathen,</hi> I ſee not how he could avoid the other, as a Faithful and True <hi>Hiſtorian.</hi>
               <pb n="107" facs="tcp:53633:62"/>
Nevertheleſs, <hi>Pliny</hi> calls him, <hi>A moſt Learned and Honeſt Author: Suidas, the famous</hi> Roman Gram<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marian: <hi>Vopiſcus, a fair, Candid and Compendious writer:</hi> But <hi>Ludo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vicus Vives</hi> ſaith, <hi>That of all the</hi> Greek <hi>and</hi> Latine Hiſtorians, <hi>He is the moſt pure and diligent, ſpeaking Truth boldly.</hi> Nay, many prefer him before <hi>Livy, Saluſt</hi> or <hi>Tacitus:</hi> which Character, though <hi>Voſſius</hi> will not aſſent to, yet doth he ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove of thoſe other Encomiums given him by <hi>Vopiſcus</hi> and <hi>Vives.</hi> This Author was at firſt rendred into <hi>Engliſh</hi> by that Voluminous Tranſlator Dr. <hi>Philemon Holland,</hi> which gave occaſion for one mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily diſpos'd to break this quibling Jeſt upon him:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Philemon</hi> with Tranſlations doth ſo fill us,</l>
                  <l>He will not let <hi>Suetonius</hi> be Tranquillus.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Juſtin?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:53633:63"/>
               <hi>Anſ. Juſtin</hi> flouriſh'd under <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius Pius,</hi> and abbreviated thoſe forty four Books of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Hiſtory</hi> of two thouſand years from <hi>Ninus</hi> to <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> which <hi>Trogus Pompejus</hi> had before compoſed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the reign of <hi>Tiberius,</hi> and where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of nothing but this <hi>Epitomy</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mains; which, nevertheleſs, we find not to occaſion the loſs of the Original, as ſome imagine. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin</hi> the <hi>Polander,</hi> as well as <hi>Munſter,</hi> confound this Author with <hi>Justin</hi> the Martyr, making them one of the ſame, becauſe they were Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temporaries; but without any colour of Reaſon, as appears by the Scurrilous Invective made by this <hi>Historian</hi> againſt the <hi>Jews,</hi> in his 36th. Book, which the Martyr would never have been guilty of. Now of this Author, as well his Method (wherein he follows his Original, even in the very number of Books) as his Stile, are both
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:53633:63"/>
highly commended. The ſeven firſt Books comprehend the Infancy of the World, or firſt Inhabitants thereof, beginning with the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of Kings, Places and Countries of the firſt <hi>Aſſyrian</hi> or <hi>Babyloniſh</hi> Monarchies; and from the ſeventh to the one and fortyeth Book, is a continued Series of the Empire of <hi>Macedon,</hi> beginning with <hi>Philip,</hi> the Father of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> the Great. He uſed no di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect Orations, for that had rendred him guilty of the ſame errour, which <hi>Trogus</hi> himſelf condemned in <hi>Livy</hi> and <hi>Salust.</hi> Yet nevertheleſs, <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtin</hi> is accuſed of ſome Digreſſions, as in the beginning of his ſecond Book, where the <hi>Scythians</hi> and <hi>Egyptians</hi> have a long tedious de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bate in preference of each others Antiquity: And likewiſe in the twentieth Book, concerning the Birth, Travels, Virtue and Death of <hi>Pythagoras.</hi> Again, <hi>Pererius</hi>
               <pb n="110" facs="tcp:53633:64"/>
in his Comment upon <hi>Daniel,</hi> hath convinc'd <hi>Juſtin</hi> of many errours concerning the <hi>Jews:</hi> And <hi>Vopiſcus</hi> accuſes him of Falſity. But that wherein he ſeems moſt of all inex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſable, is his falſe <hi>Chronology,</hi> which is wholly attributed to the Abbre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viator.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What account have you of</hi> Ammianus Marcellinus?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Ammianus Marcellinus,</hi> a <hi>Graecian</hi> and Citizen of <hi>Antioch,</hi> flouriſhed chiefly under the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours <hi>Gratian</hi> and <hi>Valentinian,</hi> holding in his youth divers conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Offices of the <hi>Militia,</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly, one of the <hi>Guard du Corps,</hi> beſides many other eminent Employs, in all which, he acquitted himſelf with much Honour. He wrote an <hi>Hiſtory</hi> which extends from the beginning of <hi>Nerva,</hi> to the death of <hi>Valens,</hi> in one and thirty Books: whereof, the firſt thirteen being loſt, the other eigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:53633:64"/>
only remain; and thoſe (too) full of Imperfection. As well his <hi>Military Profeſſion,</hi> as <hi>Greek Birth,</hi> do both contribute to the Rough<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of his Stile; and for the ſame Reaſons ought to be pardon'd. No other <hi>Hiſtorian</hi> ſo well informs us of the Antiquities and Originals of the <hi>Gauls, Germans</hi> and <hi>Burgun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dians,</hi> as he doth; neither hath any <hi>Heathen</hi> Author written leſs reflectingly on the <hi>Christians,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding the exceſſive Praiſes he attributes to <hi>Julian,</hi> which were but his due in reſpect of Moral Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues: For which reaſon, as well as for his ſincerity, and preſenting us with things no where elſe to be met with, he is duly eſteem'd of by all Learned men. Yet, nevertheleſs, ſome juſt exceptions may be taken againſt him; when, inſtead of an <hi>Historian,</hi> he plays the <hi>Philoſopher,</hi> and runs away from his Subject: As in the ſeventh Book, where he
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:53633:65"/>
quits <hi>Julian</hi> at <hi>Paris,</hi> to Speculate the nature of Earth-quakes: Alſo, in the beginning of his twentieth Book, where leaving <hi>Conſtantius</hi> to prepare againſt the <hi>Perſians,</hi> he falls enquiring into the nature of Eclipſe; and preſents his Reader with a Lecture of <hi>Aſtronomy</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>History:</hi> And again, in his thirtieth Book, where he leaves <hi>Valentinian</hi> at <hi>Tryers,</hi> whilſt he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents you with an Invective againſt <hi>Lawyers.</hi> Alſo <hi>Marcellinus</hi> is by <hi>Cauſine</hi> accuſed of his too many Poetical Deſcriptions throughout the whole Body of his Writings. But notwithſtanding all theſe Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, he is allow'd of by <hi>Voſſius, To be a Grave and Serious Writer, worthy to be beloved by all men.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div n="6" type="book">
            <pb n="113" facs="tcp:53633:65"/>
            <head>
               <hi>LIB.</hi> VI. OF GOVERNMENT AND SUCCESSION.</head>
            <p>Qu. <hi>WHich are the three prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipal forms of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, <hi>Monarchy,</hi> which is the Government of one ſingle man alone, as is uſed in <hi>England, France</hi> and <hi>Spain:</hi> Or ſecondly, an <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtocracy,</hi> where the people are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verned by a ſelect number of Noble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men or Grandees, as heretofore the States of <hi>Venice</hi> and <hi>Genoa:</hi> Or thirdly, <hi>Democracy,</hi> which is a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>publick
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:53633:66"/>
or Commonwealth, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the People are govern'd only by ſuch Magiſtrates, as they chooſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, as 'tis at this time in <hi>Holland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What are the Extreams or Abuſes of theſe three ſorts of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> When a <hi>Monarchy</hi> runs in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Tyranny, Ariſtocracy</hi> into <hi>Oli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garchy,</hi> or <hi>Democracy</hi> into <hi>Anar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy</hi> and <hi>Confuſion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How many ſorts of</hi> Monarchy <hi>are there?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Two, the one <hi>Hereditary,</hi> as in <hi>England</hi> or <hi>France,</hi> and the other <hi>Elective,</hi> as in <hi>Poland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How hath</hi> England <hi>been An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently govern'd?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. England</hi> was firſt under the <hi>Britains:</hi> ſecondly, Tributary to the <hi>Romans:</hi> thirdly, under the <hi>Saxons;</hi> fourthly, under the <hi>Danes:</hi> and fifthly under the <hi>Normans;</hi> whoſe Conqueſt of this Iſland by
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:53633:66"/>
               <hi>William</hi> Duke <hi>Normandy,</hi> is the chief Period of time from whence our <hi>Chronologers</hi> reckon.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Name me the Succeſſion of our</hi> Engliſh <hi>Monarchs from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, together with their ſeveral Races?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Firſt, of the <hi>Norman</hi> Race, were
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William</hi> the Conquerour,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>William Rufus,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt, and</item>
                  <item>King <hi>Stephen.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, of the Race of <hi>Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tagenets,</hi> were
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt,</item>
                  <item>King <hi>John,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> the third,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edward</hi> the ſecond,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edward</hi> the third, and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="116" facs="tcp:53633:67"/>Thirdly, <hi>Plantagenets</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> were
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> the fourth,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> the fifth, and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> the ſixth.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly, <hi>Plantagenets</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>York,</hi> were
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edward</hi> the fourth,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edward</hi> the fifth, and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Richard</hi> the third.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Fifthly, of the Race of <hi>Tudors,</hi> were
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth,</item>
                  <item>Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>Queen <hi>Elizabeth.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Sixthly and laſtly, of the Race of <hi>Stuarts,</hi> were
<list>
                  <item>King <hi>James,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>King <hi>Charles</hi> the Martyr, and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent King, whom God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:53633:67"/>Qu. <hi>How many years is it ſince</hi> William <hi>Duke of</hi> Normandy <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd</hi> England; <hi>or when began he to Reign?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. William</hi> the Conquerour having defeated <hi>Harold</hi> in that fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous Battle at <hi>Haſtings</hi> in <hi>Suſſex,</hi> began his Reign <hi>Anno Domini</hi> one thouſand ſixty ſix. which is about ſix hundred and ſeventeen years ago.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>When did the Diviſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the two Houſes of</hi> York <hi>and</hi> Lancaſter <hi>firſt begin?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It began upon the death of <hi>Richard</hi> the ſecond: In which Kings reign was that Inſurrection of <hi>Watt Taylor</hi> and <hi>Jack Straw,</hi> whom the Mayor of <hi>London</hi> ſo Loyally defeated.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How ended the Quarrel be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt theſe two Houſes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> By the Marriage of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, to <hi>Elizabeth</hi> the Eldeſt Daughter of <hi>Edward</hi> the Fourth;
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:53633:68"/>
which Match united the Kings <hi>Red-Roſe</hi> of <hi>Lancaster,</hi> with the Queens <hi>White-Roſe</hi> of <hi>York,</hi> and ſo eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed the Peace of both Houſes.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>From whence ſprang the Title of King</hi> James, <hi>and the</hi> Stuarts, <hi>to the Crown of</hi> England?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> By the Marriage of the Lady <hi>Margaret,</hi> King <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh's Eldeſt Daughter, to <hi>James</hi> the Fourth King of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> whoſe Son, <hi>James</hi> the fifth, had Iſſue one only Daughter, which was <hi>Mary</hi> Queen of <hi>Scots,</hi> the Mother of our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Monarch King <hi>James,</hi> the ſixth of that Name in <hi>Scotland,</hi> and the firſt in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi> For <hi>Henry</hi> the ſevenths Iſſue Male being expired by the Death of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> (the only Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lict of <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth) the next Succeſſion fell upon his Iſſue Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male, the aforeſaid Lady <hi>Margaret.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which are the chief Writers of our</hi> Engliſh Chronicles?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="119" facs="tcp:53633:68"/>
               <hi>Anſ. Matthew Paris, Matthew Westminster, Jeffry</hi> of <hi>Monmouth, Martin, Polydor Virgil, Holinshead, Speed, Stow,</hi> and <hi>Baker;</hi> beſides the Writers of particular Lives: ſuch as, <hi>Daniel, Heywood, Bacon</hi>'s <hi>Henry</hi> the ſeventh, <hi>Herbert's Henry</hi> the eighth, and <hi>Cambden</hi>'s Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> the beſt in their kind.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What Races have ſucceeded to the Crown of</hi> France?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> There have been three Races of Kings in <hi>France:</hi> The firſt of <hi>Pharamond, A. Ch.</hi> 419. the ſecond of <hi>Pepin, A. C.</hi> 751. And the third of <hi>Hugh Capet, A. C.</hi> 988.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What Races of Kings have ſucceeded to the Crown of</hi> Spain?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Since the Expulſion of the <hi>Romans,</hi> the <hi>Spaniards</hi> have had four Races of Kings: the firſt from the <hi>Goths,</hi> the ſecond, after the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vaſion of the <hi>Moors,</hi> from <hi>Don Pelago;</hi> the third from <hi>Don Sancho Mayor,</hi> King of <hi>Navarre;</hi> and the
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:53633:69"/>
fourth from the Houſe of <hi>Austria,</hi> by the Marriage of the Daughter and Heir of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the <hi>Catholick;</hi> which Race now governs in <hi>Spain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What Races of Kings have ſucceeded to the Crown of</hi> Scotland?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Ancient Kingdom of the <hi>Scots</hi> reckon by two Periods; the firſt from <hi>Ferguſius,</hi> who was King of <hi>Scotland</hi> in the time of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great; and the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond from <hi>Robert Stuart,</hi> the Son of <hi>Walter Stuart,</hi> who married <hi>Margery,</hi> King <hi>Bruces</hi> Daughter, in the year of our Lord 1350. or thereabouts.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How came</hi> Ireland <hi>into the hands of the</hi> Engliſh?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> By the Conqueſt of <hi>Henry</hi> the ſecond, in the year of Chriſt 1172.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Of what Family is the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of</hi> Germany?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Deſcended from <hi>Radulphus Auſpergenſis,</hi> who <hi>A. D.</hi> 1273. made <hi>Auſtria</hi> the Imperial Seat, conſtituting his Son <hi>Albert</hi> firſt Duke thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="121" facs="tcp:53633:69"/>Qu. <hi>Of what Family is the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour of</hi> Turkey?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Of the <hi>Ottoman</hi> Family, ſo called from the War-like Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour <hi>Othoman</hi> (Son of <hi>Orthogules</hi>) who <hi>A. D.</hi> 1300. did much enlarge the <hi>Mahometan</hi> Empire by his Arms.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Of what Family are the Kings of</hi> Portugal?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Portugal,</hi> which did for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly belong to <hi>Spain,</hi> is now a diſtinct Kingdom of it ſelf, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joys the bleſſing of Kings of its own, out of that Honourable Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of the Duke of <hi>Braganza,</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> to whom <hi>Alphonſus</hi> King of <hi>Caſtile</hi> gave his Daughter <hi>Tereſia</hi> in Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, for the good Services he had perform'd againſt the <hi>Sarazens</hi> in <hi>Portugal, A.C.</hi> 1110.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How is</hi> Holland <hi>and the</hi> Low-Countrys <hi>Governed?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Holland</hi> did formerly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long to the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> 'till by
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:53633:70"/>
the Severity of the <hi>Spaniſh Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition,</hi> and Cruel Government of the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> under <hi>Philip</hi> the ſecond, they Revolted, and by the Aſſiſtance of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> threw off the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> yoak, and ſet up a <hi>Commonwealth</hi> among them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; under which kind of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment they now continue at this very day.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What Intereſt hath the Prince of</hi> Orange <hi>in the Government af</hi> Holland?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> He is allowed a double Vote in their Senate, with many other Priviledges above the reſt, as a Reward for the good Services done them by the Old Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> in their Revolt againſt the Duke of <hi>Alva</hi> and the <hi>Spaniards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How is the preſent Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of</hi> Italy?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is divided into little <hi>Commonwealths, Principalities</hi> or <hi>Dukedoms;</hi> which in Spiritual
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:53633:70"/>
matters are moſtly ſubject to the <hi>Pope;</hi> who, as the Ghoſt of the Deceaſed <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, ſits Crown'd upon the Grave thereof, as the <hi>Malmsbury</hi> Phyloſopher well obſerves.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="7" type="book">
            <head>
               <hi>LIB.</hi> VII. OF PHYLOSOPHY.</head>
            <p>Qu. <hi>WHich are the chief Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſions of Ancient</hi> Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Theſe three; the <hi>Ionick, Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick,</hi> and <hi>Eleatick,</hi> as <hi>Clemens Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andrinus</hi> reckons them; But <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genes Laertius</hi> mentions only two the <hi>Ionick</hi> and <hi>Italick,</hi> which laſt
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:53633:71"/>
he makes to fall in with the <hi>Eleatick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Who was the firſt of the</hi> Ionick <hi>Sect?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Thales.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Who was the first of the</hi> Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick <hi>Sect?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Pythagoras;</hi> whoſe Maſters Name was <hi>Pherecydes?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What</hi> Phyloſophers <hi>ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> Thales <hi>in his Sect of</hi> Ionick Phyloſophy?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Anaximander, Anaxime<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Anaxagoras, Archelaus,</hi> and <hi>Socrates,</hi> who being the firſt Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of <hi>Moral Phyloſophy,</hi> after his time ſeveral new Sects aroſe.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Who were the chief</hi> Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers <hi>of the</hi> Italick <hi>Sect after</hi> Pytha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goras?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Telauges</hi> and <hi>Xenophanes,</hi> (whom <hi>Clemens</hi> makes the firſt of the <hi>Eleaticks,</hi>) alſo <hi>Parmenedes, Zeno Eleates, Leucippus, Empedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles, Democritus, Protagoras, Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trodorus, Diomenes, Pyrrho, Hera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clitus,
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:53633:71"/>
Anaxarchus, Nauſiphanes, Naucydes,</hi> and <hi>Epicurus,</hi> whoſe <hi>Phyloſophy</hi> is given us by the <hi>Latine</hi> Poet <hi>Lucretius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What are the chief Sects, which you ſay aroſe after</hi> Socrates, <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst his Followers?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> They were the <hi>Cynicks, Stoicks, Academicks, Peripateticks, Scepticks, Epicureans,</hi> and <hi>Eclecticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Who were the chief</hi> Cynicks?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Antisthenes, Diogenes,</hi> and <hi>Crates,</hi> from whom ſprang the <hi>Stoicks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Who were the chief</hi> Stoicks?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Crates, Zeno, Citienſis, Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anthes, Chryſippus, Cato, Varro, Tullie, Seneca, Antonius,</hi> and <hi>Poſſidonius.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Who were the chief</hi> Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demicks?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Plato, Pſeuſippus, Xenocra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes,</hi> and <hi>Polemon,</hi> of the old <hi>Aca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demy: Crantor</hi> and <hi>Arceſilaus,</hi> of the middle <hi>Academy:</hi> and <hi>Lacy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, Hegeſilans, Carneades,</hi> and <hi>Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomachus,</hi>
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:53633:72"/>
of the new <hi>Academy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Who were the chief</hi> Peripa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teticks?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Ariſtotle, Theophrastus, Stra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton, Lycon, Critolaus,</hi> and <hi>Diodorus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Who were the chief</hi> Scepticks?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Pyrrho, Timon, Aeneſidemus, Neumenius</hi> and <hi>Sextus Empericus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Who were the chief</hi> Epicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reans?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Epicurus,</hi> his ſervant <hi>Mus, Hermannus, Lucian, Celſus, Lucre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius, Caſſius</hi> who murther'd <hi>Caeſar, Maro,</hi> and <hi>Patronius Arbiter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Who were the chief</hi> Electticks?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Potamon</hi> of <hi>Alexandria, Sotion, Ammonius,</hi> and <hi>Plotinus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Why were the</hi> Cynicks <hi>ſo called?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> In deriſion of their Moroſe Dogged Manners and ill Nature; Fawning on Vertue, and Barking at Vice; as <hi>Ammonius</hi> well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſes it.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Why were the</hi> Stoicks <hi>ſo called?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="127" facs="tcp:53633:72"/>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> From the place they diſpu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in, call'd a <hi>Stoa,</hi> or <hi>Porch.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Why were the</hi> Academicks <hi>ſo called?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> From the place where they ſtudied in, called an <hi>Academy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Why were the</hi> Peripateticks <hi>ſo called?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> From their manner of Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puting as they walked in a place called the <hi>Lycaeum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Why were the</hi> Scepticks <hi>ſo called?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe they deny'd any cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainty of knowledge in any thing; which others affirming, were called <hi>Dogmaticks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Why were the</hi> Epicureans <hi>ſo called?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> From their Maſter <hi>Epicurus;</hi> who nevertheleſs received all his Principles of <hi>Atomical Phyloſophy</hi> from <hi>Democritus,</hi> who held the ſame long before.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Why were the</hi> Electicks <hi>ſo called?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="128" facs="tcp:53633:73"/>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Becauſe they pretended to ſearch all other <hi>Phyloſophies,</hi> and chooſe the beſt out of each.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Why were all theſe men called</hi> Phyloſophers?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> From their Study of Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and Knowledge.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>To what kind of knowledge did the</hi> Academicks <hi>pretend?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To know nothing certainly, but to diſpute all things; yet not abſolutely denying that there may be ſome probability of concluſion, only that it was difficult to attain unto.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>In what did the</hi> Stoicks <hi>differ from the</hi> Peripateticks, <hi>and the</hi> Epicureans <hi>from both?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Somewhat they differ'd in their <hi>Phyſicks,</hi> but moſt in their Opinions of the chief good and Happineſs of man.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Wherein did the</hi> Stoicks <hi>place Happineſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> In the rigid exerciſe of Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:53633:73"/>
and contempt of thoſe things, which others eſteem Pain or Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>In what did the</hi> Peripateticks <hi>place Happineſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> In the exerciſe of Vertue, together with the enjoyment of the gifts of Nature and Fortune; the want of which, they acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be Unhappineſs.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>In what did the</hi> Epicureans <hi>place their Happineſs?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> In the enjoyment of Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and living without the fear of Powers Inviſible.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What are the chief parts or contents of</hi> Phyloſophy?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Phyſicks,</hi> or <hi>Natural Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy; Ethicks,</hi> or <hi>Moral Phylo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſophy;</hi> and <hi>Dialecticks,</hi> or <hi>Logick.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What doth</hi> Phyſicks, <hi>or</hi> Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Phyloſophy, <hi>comprehend?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ</hi> To know the Nature of the Heavens, and all things in the World.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="130" facs="tcp:53633:74"/>Qu. <hi>What doth</hi> Ethicks, <hi>or</hi> Moral Phyloſophy, <hi>comprehend?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The inſtruction of Good Manners, Vertue and Vice, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the chief good of men, and how to attain it.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What doth</hi> Dialecticks, <hi>or</hi> Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick, <hi>teach?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The Art of Diſcourſe, or true Reaſoning, which ſerves as the Inſtrument of both the other.</p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>Which are the beſt Authors to inſtruct us in the Lives and Doctrines of the</hi> Phyloſophers?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Diogenes Laertius, Stobaeus Plutarch, Clemens Alexandrinus,</hi> and <hi>Steuchius Eugebinus;</hi> but above all, <hi>Cicero's</hi> Works, wherein we ſhall find what the Lord <hi>Bacon</hi> ſays to be Infallibly true: <hi>That as a little</hi> Phyloſophy <hi>enclineth men to</hi> Atheiſm, <hi>ſo depth in</hi> Phyloſophy <hi>bringeth back to</hi> Religion.</p>
         </div>
         <div n="8" type="book">
            <pb n="131" facs="tcp:53633:74"/>
            <head>
               <hi>LIB.</hi> VIII. Of LEARNING AND SCIENCES In General.</head>
            <p>Qu. <hi>WHich are the ſeven</hi> Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Sciences?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Philology,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Hiſtory,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Mathematicks,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Phyloſophy,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Phyſick,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Law,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Divinity.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What doth</hi> Philology <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:53633:75"/>
               <hi>Anſ. Philology</hi> comprehends the ſtudy of
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Grammar,</hi> (or the Art of Writing and Speaking Correctly;)</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Rhetorick,</hi> (or the Art of Speaking Eloquently;)</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Poetry,</hi> (or the Art of Writing in Meaſure or Verſe;)</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Logick,</hi> (or the Art of Reaſoning;)</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Anagnoſtick,</hi> (or the method of Reading Authors Profitably;)</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Criticks,</hi> (or Cenſures upon Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors;) and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Diadacticks,</hi> (or the method of Teaching others.)</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>How may</hi> Hiſtory <hi>be divided?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Into ſeven parts: As for Example,
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> (or the Hiſtory of the Fathers and Councils;)</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Political,</hi> (or the Government of States and Kingdoms;)</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Natural,</hi> (as <hi>Pliny</hi> of the Heavens, Fowls, Beaſts and Plants;)</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Succeſſions,</hi> as of Countries and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies;)</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="133" facs="tcp:53633:75"/>
                     <hi>Profeſſions,</hi> (as the Lives of Famous men in any Faculty;)</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Various,</hi> (as <hi>Aelian, Plutarchs</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, and <hi>Valerius Maximus;</hi>) and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Fabulous,</hi> (ſuch as are called <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mances;</hi>)</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What do the</hi> Mathematicks <hi>comprehend?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Arithmetick,</hi> (or the Art of Numbers;)
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Geometry,</hi> (or the Art of Meaſuring;)</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Perſpectives,</hi> (or the Art of Sight;)</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Aſtronomy,</hi> (or the knowledge of the Stars and their Motions;)</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Geography,</hi> (or the Deſcription of the Earth;)</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Architecture,</hi> (or the Art of Buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding;) and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Muſick,</hi> (or the Art of Harmony.)</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What doth</hi> Phyloſophy <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. Metaphyſicks</hi> (that treat of Supernatural things, as Spirits, &amp;c)
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Phyſicks,</hi> (or Natural Phyloſophy;)</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Ethicks,</hi> (or Moral Phyloſophy;)</item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="134" facs="tcp:53633:76"/>
                     <hi>Oeconomiques,</hi> (of Order and Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline;</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Politicks,</hi> (of Government;)</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Thanmaturgicks,</hi> (or the working Strange Concluſions;) and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pneumatology,</hi> (or the Doctrine of Spirits.)</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is comprehended in the Study of</hi> Phyſick?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To be well read in all <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural</hi> and <hi>Phyſical</hi> Writings, of the
<list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Latines,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Greeks,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Arabians,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Paracelſians,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Galeno-Chymiſts,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Prophylacticks,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Empericks.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is comprehended in the Study of</hi> Law?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To read ſuch as have written concerning <hi>Law-givers,</hi> and Laws in general,
<list>
                  <item>Of the Law of <hi>Nature,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of the Law of <hi>Nations,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <pb n="135" facs="tcp:53633:76"/>Of the Laws of the <hi>Hebrews,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of the <hi>Civil-Law,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Of the <hi>Canon-Law,</hi> and</item>
                  <item>Of our <hi>Municipal Laws.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Qu. <hi>What is comprehended in the Study of</hi> Divinity?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> To read ſuch as have writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>Divinity</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Natural,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Catechetical,</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Exegetical,</hi> on Commentators,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Polemical,</hi> in Controverſies,</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Synidetical,</hi> for Caſes of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Prophetical,</hi> of Preaching, and</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Gubernetical,</hi> of Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Inſtrue praeceptis Animum; nec diſcere Ceſſes:</l>
               <l>Nam ſine Doctrina, vita eſt qanſi Mortis Imago.</l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
